<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Speculum patrum: A looking-glasse of the Fathers wherein, you may see each of them drawn, characterized, and displayed in their colours. To which are added, the characters of some of the chief philosophers, historians, grammarians, orators, and poets. By Edward Larkin, late Fellow of Kings Colledge in Cambridge, and now minister of the Word at Limesfield in Surrey.</title>
            <author>Larkin, Edward, 1623-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88705</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L444A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230373</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896264</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896264</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154025</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88705)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154025)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2393:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Speculum patrum: A looking-glasse of the Fathers wherein, you may see each of them drawn, characterized, and displayed in their colours. To which are added, the characters of some of the chief philosophers, historians, grammarians, orators, and poets. By Edward Larkin, late Fellow of Kings Colledge in Cambridge, and now minister of the Word at Limesfield in Surrey.</title>
                  <author>Larkin, Edward, 1623-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 99, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for H.E. and are to be sold by Iohn Sprat bokseller [sic] neer the signe of the Castle in Norwich,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Characters of the Fathers.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Skakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fathers of the church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154025:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154025:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154025:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154025:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Speculum Patrum: A LOOKING-GLASSE OF THE FATHERS, WHEREIN, You may ſee each of them drawn, Characterized, and Diſplayed in their colours.</p>
            <p>To which are added, The Characters of ſome of the Chief <hi>Philoſophers, Hiſtorians, Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, Orators,</hi> and <hi>Poets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY <hi>EDWARD LARKIN,</hi> Late Fellow of Kings Colledge in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and now Miniſter of the Word at <hi>Limesfield</hi> in <hi>Surrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>H.E.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Iohn Sprat</hi> Bokſeller neer the Signe of the Caſtle in <hi>Norwich.</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:154025:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154025:3"/>
            <head>To his moſt Honoured Friend, <hi>Marmaduke Greſham</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> of <hi>NEWHALL</hi> at <hi>Limesfield</hi> in <hi>Surrey.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>GReat favours do oblige to great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments: You have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant to me in the one, and I ſhould appear vilely ingrateful, ſhould I be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective to you in the other. Wherefore, though it is not within the ſphere of my power propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably to requite your goodneſs, yet it ſhall ever be within the circumference of my will to remember it. <hi>Pertinax ſit memoria deben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> was excellent good advice, though from the mouth of a Heathen: Hence <hi>Seneca</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares the Graces to youthful Maidens, and the reaſon of that parallel he ſaith is this, <hi>quia non debet beneficiorum memoria ſeneſcere,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Records of benefits conferred, muſt never wax old. That was a good expreſſion of one in <hi>Euripides,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>I hate the thanks of ſuch friends as wither with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:154025:4"/>
            <p>For this cauſe therefore have I preſented your fair hands with this ſmall Treatiſe, to let the world know of your engagements on me, and my readineſs to make ſuch requital, as my poor capacity enables me to return. <hi>Reddit bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium qui libenter debet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I doubt not of your kinde acceptance of this mean Miſſive, with us much generous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, as my heart offers it with cordial alacrity. And what is wanting in my ſhort and ſtreightned compenſations, I ſhall beſeech God to enlarge and make complete by his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings. It is <hi>symmachus</hi> his expreſſion, <hi>Pro beneficiis ſi non ſimus ſolvendo, coeleſtibus delegamus virtutibus:</hi> So that I hope I may ſay with <hi>Auſonius, Tibi coepit Deus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere pro nobis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I ſhall not trouble you with more words, onely give me leave to adde this, That I am yours in a thouſand bonds, and muſt ever remain bound to reverence your Perſon, and love your Vertues. This is the Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your unfeigned faithful Servant,</hi> Edward Larkin.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Limesfield,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Novemb. 29. 1658.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154025:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>SPECULUM PATRUM,</hi> A LOOKING-GLASSE OF THE FATHERS, Wherein you may ſee each of them characterized and diſplayed in their colours.</head>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the <hi>Areopagite.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Apoſtles being all withdrawn from the Church Militant, and made free Deniſons of the Triumphant, our Saviour now reigning in heaven, raiſed up many eminent and burning Lights, whereby he ſpread his glorious Goſpel through all the parts
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154025:5"/>of the Univerſe: Amongſt which <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the <hi>Areopagite</hi> is to be taken notice of, as one of the firſt Stars which appeared: He had that name given him, in that before his converſion he was a Judge of criminal cauſes at <hi>Athens:</hi> He was one of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Auditors, from whom, as his Nurſe, he ſuckt the milk of Chriſtian Religion, at what time the good Apoſtle was at the Academy of <hi>Athens</hi> diſputing with the Ethnick Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, as his Lord and Maſter had done before with the Jewiſh Rabbines and Doctors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Nicephorus</hi> write of him, that he was Biſhop of <hi>Athens,</hi> from whence he was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward removed, if we may give credit to <hi>Baronius,</hi> to the Biſhoprick of <hi>Paris</hi> in <hi>France.</hi> This grave man being full of dayes, and as full of divine Grace, was crowned with the lawrel of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, not in <hi>Domitian</hi>'s time, (as ſome think) but in the reign of the Emperour <hi>Trajan,</hi> of whom it may be ſaid, that he was a good Prince to all but his Chriſtian Subjects, whoſe holy profeſſion ſeemed to the worlds eye, therefore, to be the more odious, becauſe ſo juſt a Prince as <hi>Trajan</hi> ſeem'd to be, did not forbear to perſecute it.</p>
               <p>When this <hi>Dionyſius</hi> was in <hi>Egypt,</hi> whither he withdrew himſelf for the ſtudy of Philoſophy, and had there taken notice of that miraculous Eclipſe, which happened at our Saviours Paſſion, whereof he could find no natural reaſon, he cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, <hi>Aut Deus Naturae patitur, aut mandi ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>china diſſolvetur:</hi> Either the God of Nature ſuffereth, or the whole frame and fabrick of the world will be inſtantly diſſolved.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:154025:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicephorus</hi> and <hi>Suidas</hi> give us a catalogue of this mans Works, which <hi>Baronius</hi> labours to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, but other learned Writers, ſuch as <hi>Laurentius Valla,</hi> and <hi>Eraſmus: Luther, Cajetan,</hi> and our Engliſh <hi>Whitaker,</hi> prove them by many arguments to be ſuppoſititions and counterfeit.</p>
               <p>His received Works we have printed in two Tomes at <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> with the Scholiaſts of <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> and the Paraphraſe of <hi>Pachimaera</hi> in the year of Chriſt 1634.</p>
               <p>I meet with two Eulogies given to this Father, the one is from <hi>Trithemius,</hi> who cals him. <hi>Virum eximiae ſanctitatis, &amp; incomparabilis doctrinae;</hi> a man of tranſcendent ſanctity, and incomparable learning.</p>
               <p>The other is from <hi>Sixtus Senenſis,</hi> who ſaies this of him, <hi>Quod divinae &amp; in myſteriis abſconditae ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientiae admiranda volumina graeco, &amp; ſublimi elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quio doctiſſime conſcripſit;</hi> That he wrote in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime Greek language admirable volumes of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and myſterious wiſdome: And ſo he gives you a Schedule of all his works, as they were approved by the third Council of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Campian</hi> the Jeſuite in his fifth Reaſon, pag. 32. ſpeaks thus of this <hi>Dionyſius</hi> his Hierarchy, <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſii Areopagitae Hierarchia, quas claſſes, quae ſacra, quos ritus edocet?</hi> And out of the ſame book this Jeſuite proves both Purgatory, and their Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Eccleſiaſtical Hierarchy: But that work is none of this <hi>Dionyſius</hi>'s, though it bear his name; and this you have juſtified by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154025:6"/>
                  <hi>Sixtus Senenſis,</hi> and ſeverall other learned Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Ignatius.</head>
               <p>THe next to <hi>Dionyſius</hi> is <hi>Ignatius,</hi> the ſecond Biſhop of <hi>Antioch</hi> after <hi>Peter,</hi> as <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Nicephorus</hi> relate: He had that name given him, <hi>ab igne charitatis,</hi> from the fire of charity wherewith he burned. He was alſo called, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, either becauſe he was born of God, or elſe in regard of his bearing God in his pure and holy heart. This eminent Champion was thrown to hungry Lyons in that perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which <hi>Trajan</hi> ſtirred up againſt the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scaliger</hi> gives him this commendation, <hi>Vir (quod in orientis partibus per-rarum eſt) ſingulari eruditione;</hi> A man (which is very rare in the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern parts) of ſingular erudition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> mentioning him writes thus, <hi>Ignatius amongſt moſt men famous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neander</hi> in his Geography, part 2. moſt highly extols him in theſe or ſuch like expreſſions, <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Antiochenae Eccleſiae praefuit, vir magni ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſidei, &amp; zeli; Ignatius</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> a man of great ſpirit, faith and zeal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baronius</hi> ſpeaking of the Epiſtles which this man ſhould write, he ſtiles them, <hi>Copiam Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicarum
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154025:6"/>traditionum apothecam, fortemque ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus haereticos armaturam;</hi> A copious ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of Apoſtolical traditions, and a ſtrong ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour againſt hereticks.</p>
               <p>This Father was wont to ſay (when he ſpake of our Saviours death and paſſion) that his Love was crucified. <hi>Ireneus</hi> gives us an account of his Martyrdome, and ſets down the very words he ſhould utter a little before his ſufferings, which were to this effect or ſenſe: <hi>Inaſmuch as I am the wheat of God, I am to be ground with the teeth of beaſts, that I may be found pure bread, or fine manchet.</hi> His Epiſtles were printed at <hi>Oxford,</hi> 1644.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Polycarpus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>POlycarpus</hi> (whoſe name ſignifieth much fruit; was the Diſciple of St. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Apoſtle, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by him Biſhop of the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi>) he went to <hi>Rome</hi> in the reign of <hi>Antonius Pius</hi> (<hi>Anicetus</hi> being Prelate at that time there) where he reduced to the true faith thoſe which were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched by the hereticks <hi>Marcion</hi> and <hi>Valentinus:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It happened, that wicked <hi>Marcion</hi> there meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him, thus ſpake to him, <hi>Knoweſt thou us, O Polycarpus?</hi> To whom forthwith this grave and holy man moſt diſdainingly anſwered, <hi>I know thee to be the firſt-born of the Devil.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:154025:7"/>
               <p>This godly Profeſſor was in the dayes of <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninus</hi> the Philoſopher, and <hi>Lucius Verus,</hi> Roman Emperors, tied to a ſtake in the midſt of the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phitheater, and there devoured by the mercileſſe flames, as <hi>Volaterrane</hi> and <hi>Euſebius</hi> have written; but others yet ſay, that he could not burn, the Lord from Heaven reſtraining the natural violence of the fire by a miracle, and thereupon they ſlew him with the ſword at <hi>Smyrna,</hi> in the year of our Lord, 167.</p>
               <p>In this mans time <hi>Egeſippus</hi> the <hi>Iew</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to the Chriſtian Faith, who afterward wrote in five books, the Hiſtory of the Church from Chriſt to his own time. This <hi>Polycarpus</hi> writ an Epiſtle to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> ſo ſaith <hi>Ierome,</hi> and another to great <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the <hi>Areopagite;</hi> ſo <hi>Suidas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Socrates</hi> in his Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory tels us, That this man did communicate with <hi>Anicetus</hi> the Roman Biſhop, though he differed in opinion from him, about the celebration of <hi>Eaſter. Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus</hi> commends that Epiſtle of his to the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians</hi> in his third book againſt hereſies, ſaying, That <hi>it is ſo full furniſhed to this, that out of it all thoſe, which have any care of their ſalvation, may know the character of faith, and the doctrine of truth. Euſebius</hi> recites the Prayer which this holy and devout man did conceive and utter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately before he was martyred; it begins thus, <hi>O Father of thy beloved and bleſſed Son Ieſus Chriſt, by whom we have knowledge of thee</hi>—</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:154025:7"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ireneus</hi> gives this eminent Saint this following commendation; <hi>Hic docuit ſemper, quae ab Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolis didicerat, &amp; Eccleſiae tradidit quae ſola ſunt vera;</hi> This man alwayes taught that which he had learnt of the Apoſtles, and delivered to the Church thoſe things which are only true. 'Tis <hi>Dalleus</hi> his Blogy of him, <hi>Quo viro poſt Apoſtolos, quorum familiaris fuit, vix ullus apud Chriſtianos unquam fuit ſanctior, ant divinior;</hi> Then which man after the Apoſtles (whoſe familiar compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion he was) there was ſcarce any one among the Chriſtians more holy and divine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> gives us an account of his martyrdom by an Epiſtle of the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> inſerted in his Hiſtory, wherein we have many remarkable paſſages; one is a Voice ſpeaking to <hi>Polycarpe</hi> from Heaven, and ſaying thus, <hi>O</hi> Polycarpe <hi>be of courage, and play the man,</hi> even then when he was ſtanding before the Judgement-ſeat. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the ſtout Reply, which he made the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſul, when he tempted him to deny the Lord Jeſus, which was much to this effect, <hi>Fourſcore and five years have I ſerved him, neither hath he ever offended me, and how can I revile my King, who hath hitherto kept me.</hi> A third is, that when his body was burning, it ſeemed to the ſenſes of them that beheld it, to ſend forth a ſweet and fragrant ſmell, as of Frankincenſe, or ſuch like odoriferous perfume.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:154025:8"/>
               <head>Justine Martyr.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IUſtine Martyr</hi> fiouriſhed in the reign of <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Pius,</hi> and ſo was contemporary with <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carpe. Euſebius</hi> in his Eccleſiaſtical hiſtory ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him ſaith, that this man was famous in the Chriſtian Doctrine a little after the times of the Apoſtles: He was the ſon of <hi>Priſcas Bacchus,</hi> born at <hi>Flavia,</hi> a new City of <hi>Syria Paleſtina,</hi> ſo he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf tels us, in one of his Apologies. Its ſaid, that the Emperour upon his reading of this mans Apologies, which he had dedicated to him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he pleaded the righteous cauſe of poor diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and calamitous Chriſtians, that he gave order for the ceaſing of the perſecution. <hi>Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Suidas</hi> doe ſpeak great matters in the honour and praiſe of this Champion. He wrote againſt the Heretick <hi>Marcion,</hi> whoſe venome (it ſeems) had ſpread it ſelf farre and wide in his dayes.</p>
               <p>He was a notable Philoſopher, and in his Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue with <hi>Trypho</hi> he ſaith, that he had been an Auditor of all the Sects of them, of <hi>Stoicks, Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pateticks, Pythagoreans,</hi> and <hi>Platonicks. Ierome</hi> tels us in his Catalogue of Eccleſiaſtical Writers, that he did, <hi>habitu Philoſophico incedere,</hi> walk in the guiſe and habit of a Philoſopher. He was beheaded at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſaith <hi>Euſebius,</hi> in the reign of <hi>Lucius Verus,</hi> but according to <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> it was before, even in the time of <hi>Adrian.</hi> His death,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154025:8"/>whenſoever it was, was promoted and procured by the malice and revenge of <hi>Creſcens</hi> an ungodly Philoſopher, who being worſted by him in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent diſputations, never left till his malignancy had brought to paſſe this pious Martyrs deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: whence you have this or the like paſſage from his own mouth in his Apologie, relating to his perſecutor <hi>Creſcens; I look for no other thing then this, that I be betrayed by ſome one of them called Philoſophers, or knockt in the head by</hi> Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens, <hi>no Philoſopher indeed, but only a proud ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited boaſter</hi>— and ſo he goes on in that Apology.</p>
               <p>This Father records of himſelf, that he was prevailed withall, and won to imbrace the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, through the cruelties of heathen Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants againſt the Saints of Chriſt, and their coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious patience under them. We meet with a worthy character given this man, in the <hi>Biblio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theca</hi> of <hi>Photius,</hi> which is as followeth, or much to that ſenſe; <hi>Eſt vir ille ad Philoſophiae tum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae, tum potiſſimum profanae ſummum evectus fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigium, multipliciſque eruditionis &amp; hiſtoriarum copia circumfluens;</hi> That man is an eminent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient both in our Chriſtian Philoſophy, and alſo in prophane, and overflowing with abundance of various learning and hiſtories. <hi>Pareus</hi> ſaith this of his works, <hi>quod ejuſdem ſcripta etiamnum cum fructu leguntur;</hi> That his writings are now read with benefit. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> cals him, <hi>Virum ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, &amp; Dei amantem,</hi> a holy man, and a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of God. <hi>Tatianus</hi> in his book againſt the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154025:9"/>Gentiles, ſtiles him <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, moſt admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
               <p>Yet this man, though he did apologize for Chriſtianity, had his errors. In his Dialogue with <hi>Trypho</hi> he ſhews himſelf an Abetter of the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the <hi>Chiliaſts;</hi> and the barbarous Gentiles he did entitle to ſalvation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>A thenagoras.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Thenagoras</hi> a Philoſopher of <hi>Athens</hi> turned Chriſtian, and flouriſhed, if we may believe <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> in the year of Chriſt, 142. when <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius Pius</hi> was Emperour, and <hi>Teleſphorus</hi> the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Biſhop; though <hi>Baronius</hi> will not have him to appear till the year of our Lord 179. which was the time, when <hi>Aurelius</hi> ſat in the Throne, and <hi>Soter</hi> or <hi>Eleutherius</hi> in the Chair. He was a man of very gteat eſteem with the ſaid Prince for his vaſt abilities and profound learning; he wrote an Apology in the behalf of his fellow Chriſtians, and likewiſe undertook an Embaſſie, that he might ſpeak as an Advocate for them to the Roman Majeſty.</p>
               <p>He publiſhed a golden book (as one cals it) of the Reſurrection, ſet out and interpreted by <hi>Andreas Geſner. Epiphanius</hi> cites this mans Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy in the Hereſie of <hi>Origen,</hi> where he relates the words of <hi>Proclus</hi> out of <hi>Methodius. Bellarmine</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:154025:9"/>in his book of Eccleſiaſtical Writers ſaith, <hi>Scripto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem hunc carere ſuſpicione;</hi> That this Writer is without ſuſpition, and yet he is conſtrained to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that he was over-paſſed both by <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Ierome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Varro</hi> ſaith; that this Author writ alſo ſome books of Husbandry: How he dyed I read not, what is now extant of his Works you have print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in one volume with <hi>Iuſtine Martyr.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Irenaeus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IRenaeus</hi> flouriſhed, ſay ſome, about the 160. year of Chriſt, others the 180. when <hi>Aurelius An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius</hi> and <hi>Commodus</hi> were Emperours, and in that he ſaith, that in his childhood he converſt with <hi>Polycarpus</hi> ſome of the learned think, that he was born either at <hi>Smyrna,</hi> or not far from it, that he was a Greek his name is their warrant to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith, that he ſucceeded <hi>Pothinus</hi> in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Lyons,</hi> where he governed the Church (ſay ſome) for thirty years, others ſay more: Some which have written Martyrologies, ſpeaking of his death, doe tell us, that he was butchered by the Tyrant <hi>Maximinus,</hi> who was a great perſecutor of the Saints and people of God. <hi>Bargnius</hi> ſaith, that he was martyred with almoſt all his people of <hi>Lyons,</hi> in that horrid ſtorm, which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154025:10"/>was raiſed againſt the Chriſtians by the Emperour <hi>Severus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He wrote againſt the hereſies of thoſe times, which Satan had ſpread abroad, on purpoſe to eclipſe, if not altogether to extinguiſh, the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of the Truth. He was at <hi>Rome</hi> with <hi>Eleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therius,</hi> where he indeavoured the conviction of <hi>Blaſtus</hi> and <hi>Florinus</hi> two notable Schiſmaticks, and to allay that malignant ſpirit of error which their ſtinking breath had raiſed. He alſo ſharply reyroved the Roman Biſhop <hi>Victor,</hi> for that he had injuriouſly excommunicated the Aſian Churches, ſo ſaith <hi>Euſebius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eraſmus</hi> thinks that this Author wrote in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, and not in Greek, and being skilled in Greek, he therefore uſeth Graeciſmes: But <hi>Rhenanus</hi> judges the contrary, becauſe <hi>Ierome</hi> reckons him among the Grecian Writers. <hi>Tertullian</hi> doth beſtow on this man this following admirable cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter; Irenaeus, <hi>omnium doctrinarum curioſiſſimus explorator;</hi> A moſt exquiſite and curious ſearcher into all manner and kind of learning. <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> cals him, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Moſt bleſſed and moſt holy <hi>Ireneus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in an Epiſtle of his thus ſets him forth; firſt he commends him from his name, <hi>Magnus ille Eccleſiae propugnator, pro ſui nominis augurio, pacis Eccleſiae vindex;</hi> and then he goes on, highly extolling his writings, <hi>ſpirant illius ſcripta priſcum illum Evangelii vigorem, ac phraſis arguit pectus martyrio paratum, habent enim Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres ſuam quandam dictionem ſeriam, fortem &amp;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154025:10"/>maſculam;</hi> That great defender of the Church, for the divination of his name, a maintainer of the Churches peace; his writings breath that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient vigour of the Goſpel, and his phraſe argues a heart prepared for martyrdome; for Martyrs have a certain ſerious expreſſion, valiant and maſculine. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſpeaking of the books which this man wrote, ſaith of them, <hi>Quod pleni ſum doctrina &amp; pietate,</hi> that they are full of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and piety.</p>
               <p>Yet notwithſtanding this great Light had his eclipſes, as appears by ſomewhat that is unſound in his own writings. Particularly he was entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with the ſnare of <hi>Papias,</hi> who was the Father of the <hi>Chiliaſts;</hi> this <hi>Euſebius</hi> doth charge him with, as we find it in the third book of his hiſtory, the ſix and thirtieth chapter, againſt which opinion of his, <hi>Dionyſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> is ſaid to have written ſomewhat in confutation, ſo ſaith <hi>Sixtus Senenſis.</hi> He was likewiſe once an allower of free-will in ſpirituals, though afterwards he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed himſelf to the contrary, ſaying, <hi>Non a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, ſed a Deo eſſe bonum ſalutis noſtrae,</hi> that our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is not from our ſelves but God.</p>
               <p>There was one ſtrange opinion more to which he was addicted, and that was, <hi>Animas a corpore ſeparatas habere hominis figuram &amp; characterem corporis, ut etiam cognoſcantur,</hi> That ſouls departed and ſeparated from the body, have mans figure and form of his body, ſo that they may be known by it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:154025:11"/>
               <head>Pantaenus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PAntaenus</hi> was of the School of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> where at firſt he profeſſed the Philoſophy of the Stoicks, but afterwards became very eminent in the profeſſion of Chriſtian Divinity. Its ſaid of him by learned <hi>Pareus, Quod primus ſcholam ex ethnica in chriſtianaem mutavit;</hi> that he was the firſt which changed an ethnick ſchool into a chriſtian. He was ſent from <hi>Alexandria</hi> by <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrianus</hi> the Biſhop thereof, into <hi>India,</hi> to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh that church in the ſacred Truth, which the Apoſtles of our Lord Jeſus had there planted; where meeting with the Goſpel of St. <hi>Matthew</hi> written in Hebrew, and left there with thoſe Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern people by <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> he brought it thence (ſay ſome) to the City of <hi>Alexandria.</hi> though <hi>Euſebius</hi> tels us, that it remained there, even in his time.</p>
               <p>He was the Maſter of that famous Schollar <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> he flouriſhed under the Emperours <hi>Severus</hi> and <hi>Antonius Caracalla,</hi> about the year of Chriſt 200. he left behind him ſome certain Commentaries on the holy Scripture, which are not now extant, though <hi>Ierome</hi> had in his time the knowledge of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſtiles him, a famous learned man, and one in great eſtimation, <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. and <hi>Senen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> ſpeaking of him, tels us, that he was eminent, <hi>propter tam ſecularis literaturae, quam ſacrae erudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:154025:11"/>gloriam,</hi> as well for the glory of his ſecular learning as his ſacred erudition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Clemens Alexandrinus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CLemens Alexandrinus,</hi> (So called, becauſe he was a Presbyter of <hi>Alexandria</hi>) preached the Goſpel both at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and at <hi>Antioch;</hi> he was the maſter of <hi>Origen,</hi> and moderated in the School of <hi>Alexandria</hi> after <hi>Pantaenus.</hi> He flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in the raign of <hi>Severus</hi> and his ſon <hi>Antoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi> He wrote many learne books, <hi>Euſebius</hi> calls him, <hi>in Divinis Scripturis exercitatum,</hi> one exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in the Divine Scriptures. <hi>Cauſabon, inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſtae Doctrinae virum,</hi> a man of unexhauſted learning. <hi>Heniſius Penu eruditionis, &amp; Seientiae.</hi> The granary of Erudition and Science. <hi>Cauſſinus Plutarchum Chriſtianum,</hi> The Chriſtian Plutark, <hi>Dempſter, gravem &amp; diſertum authorem,</hi> A grave and eloquent author, but the Centuriators of of <hi>Magdeburg</hi> are full and large in his Character, which we have from them as followeth; <hi>Fuit in hoc homine omnino Ingens diſcendi cupiditas, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genium acutum, tenaciſſima memoria, Fervens Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Gloriae Dei, &amp; Religionis Chriſtianae, ut ex ſuis Scriptis conſpici poteſt, maximae eruditionis, Zeli, facundiae, ac proinde etiam authoritatis, ſed etiam Scriptis tum toti Eccleſiae ſui Aevi, tum etiam poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritati in perpetuum profuit.</hi> There was in this man
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154025:12"/>altogether a vaſt deſire of learning, an acute wit, a moſt tenacious memorie, a fervent zeal of Gods glory and the Chriſtian Religion, as may be ſeen out of his writings, of very great erudition, zeal, eloquence, and ſo alſo of authority; neither did he onely advantage his Auditors by his voice, but likewiſe by his writings, both the whole Church of his age, as alſo poſterity throughout all ages.</p>
               <p>This man with his Maſter <hi>Pantaenus,</hi> is reported to have been the firſt founders of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Academies, for they delivered the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals of Heavenly truth, not by ſermons to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but by Catechiſticall doctrine to the learned in the Schooles. S. <hi>Ierom</hi> ſaith this of this mans Workes; <hi>Feruntur ejus inſignia volumina, plena<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eruditionis, &amp; eloquentiae, tam de Scripturis Divinis, quam de ſecularis literaturae inſtrumento.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet this man had too high an eſteem of Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereby it hapned, that he fell into vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, errours, amongſt which, he affirmed, <hi>That afterour calling to the Knowledge of the truth, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly God might grant to them that have ſinned, a recovery into their former ſtate for once, or twice by repentance, but if they ſhould fall oftner into ſin then ſo, there is no more reſtitution to be expected or hoped for, but a fearfull looking for a finall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> And yet afterward forgetting this his aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he ſaith in his fourth book of Strom. <hi>That Whenſoever ſinners do repent, whether here in this world, or elſe in the next, they may be received to Gods mercy.</hi> In which paſſage of his, he ſeems to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154025:12"/>inſinuate that men may repent, and ſo finde favour at the hands of God, after that this preſent life is determined. Then which Poſition, there is nothing more contrary to the Scripture, and likewiſe to his own forementioned, and foregoing expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>Moreover, he delivered, lib. 7. Strom. <hi>That the law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>was ſufficient to the Iewes, and to the Heathens or Gentiles, their Philoſophy before Chriſts coming, to ſalvation.</hi> In his firſt Book, you have theſe words touching the Juſtification of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Philoſophy heretofore did of its own nature juſtifie the Greeks.</hi> You have an enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all this mans errours from <hi>Chemnitius</hi> in the firſt part of his Examen, pag. 78. He dyed at <hi>Alexandria</hi> where he taught, ſo ſaith <hi>Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Origenes Adamantius.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ORigenes Adamantius,</hi> flouriſhed (ſay ſome) vnder <hi>Gallus</hi> and <hi>Voluſian,</hi> others, under <hi>Galienus,</hi> and <hi>Valerian.</hi> He was the ſon of <hi>Leoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> and diſciple of <hi>Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> he firſt taught by way of Catechizing, when he was but aged eighteen yeers, and ſaith one of him, <hi>Quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum docuit, ſic vixit, &amp; quemadmodum vixit, ſic docuit.</hi> As he taught ſo he lived, and as he lived,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154025:13"/>ſo he taught; When he was but a child, he encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged his father to continue conſtant in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian cauſe, himſelf being forward to ſeal it with his own blood, if his mother had not (as <hi>Euſebius</hi> records) prevented him in it. <hi>Ierome</hi> in his Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of Illuſtrious Writers, relates this of him, in commendation of his great learning, that he read publike Lectures in theſe following ſciences: Logick, Geometry, Arithmetike, Muſick, Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Rethorick, and other Philoſophicall diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plines.</p>
               <p>When he was but a youth, he would ſearch very narrowly into the ſence of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; which his father <hi>Leonides</hi> obſerving, would now and then gently reprove him in theſe or the like expreſſions; <hi>Nequid ſupra aetatens quaeras.</hi> Dive not into that myſtery, which is out of the reach of thy youthfull yeers to comprehend: And yet coming to his bedſide at night, and uncovering his breaſt, he would kindly kiſſe it, judgeing himſelf moſt happy in this, that he had ſo gracious a ſon? Some write that he made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf an Eunuch for chaſtities ſake. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of him, that he wrote 6000. volumes; <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pera ejus aſcendunt ad ſena millia librorum,</hi> and tis <hi>Ieroms; Quis noſtrum tanta poteſt legere, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ille conſcripſit.</hi> Which of ours can read ſo much as he hath written.</p>
               <p>Its an ancient obſervation concerning this Father. <hi>Origenes ubi bene Scripſit, nemo melius; ubi male, nemo peius.</hi> Where <hi>Origen</hi> wrote well, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wrote better, where ill, none worſe. Whence for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154025:13"/>ſome errors he is reckoned by ſome Authors in the number of Heriticks. <hi>Vincentius Lyrinenſis</hi> tels us, <hi>Errorem</hi> Originis <hi>propter ejus tum doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, tum zelum, magnam in Dei Eccleſia fuiſſe ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationem;</hi> That the errour of <hi>Origen,</hi> both for his learning and zeal, was a great temptation in the the Church of God.</p>
               <p>He was called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the books he did compile and ſet out, which he ever writ ſtanding. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, that all the latter Doctors of the Church were much further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by this mans works; whence 'tis ſaid (as it is in <hi>Suidas</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Origen</hi> the whet-ſtone of us all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ierome</hi> ſtiles him, <hi>Sacrorum omnium expoſitorum victorem,</hi> the victor of all ſacred Expoſitors. Eraſmus, <hi>Theologorum ſine controverſia principem,</hi> of Divines the chief without controverſie. And <hi>Poſſevinus</hi> ſpeaking of his works, ſaith of them, <hi>In qua parte probantur, neminem poſt Apoſtolos ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit aequalem,</hi> in them, which are approved, he had none after the Apoſtles his equal: Yet however, ſome there be, that doe debaſe him. <hi>Baſil</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges him, that he had not a ſound opinion of the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Ierome</hi> cals his opinions, <hi>Venenata dogmata, &amp; aliena Scripturis, &amp; vim facientia Scripturis,</hi> invenomed opinions, erring from the Scriptures, and doing them violence: <hi>Cauſabon</hi> will have him accounted a Platonick Philoſopher, rather than a Divine. <hi>Ribera</hi> ſtiles him, <hi>Arii patrem, &amp; aliarum hereſew radicem,</hi> the father of <hi>Arius,</hi> and the root of all hereſies, out of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:154025:14"/>
                  <hi>Epiphanius.</hi> He dyed at <hi>Tyre</hi> in the year of his age 69.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Tertullian.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TErtullian</hi> of <hi>Carthage</hi> in <hi>Affrica</hi> firſt ſtudied Philoſophy, and the Civil Law, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards addicted himſelf to the ſtudy of Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie; he was the ſon of a Centurion, called <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens,</hi> from the habit or garb of his body; he was a man of admirable parts, and moſt piercing wit, excelling in the knowledge of the Greek and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine tongues; he flouriſhed when <hi>Alexander Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verus</hi> and <hi>Antonius Caracalla</hi> were Emperours. At firſt he was a Prieſt at <hi>Rome,</hi> where he continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the midſt of his years, and then being driven thence, he returned to <hi>Carthage,</hi> where for a time he maintained the damnable opinion of the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick <hi>Montanus,</hi> but at laſt, ſome ſay, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canted and renounc'd it.</p>
               <p>He waged many diſputes with the <hi>Iews,</hi> and with thoſe deteſtable inſtruments of Satan, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly <hi>Marcion, Valentinus</hi> the Gentile, wicked <hi>Hermogenes,</hi> and <hi>Praxeas;</hi> he lived till he was very aged. So admired (ſaith <hi>Ierome</hi>) he was of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> that not a day paſſed without his read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome portion of his works, it being his uſual ſpeech, <hi>Da mihi Magiſtrum,</hi> give me my Maſter. The learned have afforded him many excellent
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:154025:14"/>Eulogies: <hi>Omni literarum genere peritus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lactantius,</hi> skill'd in every kind of learning. Yertullianus <hi>mihi certe, ter</hi> Tullius, <hi>&amp; Roſa eſt,</hi> ſaith another; and tis <hi>Lypſius</hi> his commendation,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quis poſt Tertullianum inter ſacros ſcriptores doctior?</hi> who amongſt the ſacred writers was after <hi>Tertullian</hi> more learned? And as another of the Criticks ſpeaks, <hi>eruditiſſimus, &amp; quantum patitur aetas illa &amp; patria Affrica, eloquentiſſimus,</hi> moſt learned, and as much as that age, and his countrey Affrick doth permit, moſt eloquent.</p>
               <p>Yet this man was carryed away with ſtrange errors, whence <hi>Ierome</hi> could ſay, <hi>in Tertulliano laudamus ingenium, ſed damnamus Haereſin,</hi> we commend <hi>Tertullians</hi> wit, but we condemn his hereſie.</p>
               <p>He attributed a body to God, he condemned ſecond marriage; he aſſerted that the ſonne had a beginning, <hi>tempus fuit, cum filius non fuit,</hi> are his own words, in his book againſt <hi>Hermogenes,</hi> not far from the beginning; which is the very phraſe of <hi>Speech</hi> uſed by the heretick <hi>Arius.</hi> After bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme he allowed but onely one repentance; he gave too much to the power of mans will, he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed remiſſion of ſins to humane ſatisfactions, and laſtly he was a Chiliaſt, no wonder then if his authority be ſo little ſet by of many. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects his teſtimony, and undervalues his authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in many of his writings: in one place this he ſayes of him, <hi>Tertullianus haereſiarcha fuit, Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> was a principal, or Arch-heretick; in another,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:154025:15"/>this, <hi>Euſebii, &amp; Tertulliani, parva autoritas; Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> and <hi>Tertullians</hi> authority is but ſmall, and beſides <hi>Bellarmine, Lirinenſis</hi> ſtiles him, <hi>univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalis ac vetuſtae fidei parum tenacem, ac diſertiorem nullo, quam fideliorem,</hi> one that hath little hold of the univerſal, and ancient faith, and much more eloquent then faithful! and <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, that he was the head of a new ſect, which were called Tertullianiſts: ſome tell us, that he was deſirous of Martyrdome, but of what kind of death he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, no author doth certainly report it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Gregorius Thaumaturgus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GRegorius Thaumaturgus,</hi> this man had ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name, <hi>Euſebius</hi> calls him <hi>Theodorus</hi> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>Athenodorus,</hi> he was drawn from the ſtudy of the Greek and Roman diſcipline, and from the love of Philoſophy, to the ſtudy of the holy Scripture, that true divine Philoſophy indeed, by the miniſtry of <hi>Origen,</hi> of whom he was a zealous auditor, whilſt he with many others flockt to him, preaching at <hi>Caeſarea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> tells us, that he, and his brother were ordained Biſhops of certain Churches in <hi>Pontus,</hi> he uſually paſſes under the title of <hi>Epiſcopus Neo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caeſarienſis,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Neocaeſarea;</hi> they ſay that he wrought many miracles, whence he had the name of <hi>Thaumaturgus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:154025:15"/>
               <p>He was preſent at the council of <hi>Antioch</hi> againſt <hi>Samoſatenus,</hi> that Arch-heretick, as <hi>Pareus</hi> calls him: he was eminent in the raign of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Severus,</hi> he wrote an oration in the praiſe of his maſter <hi>Origen,</hi> ſtiled by <hi>Sixtus Senenſis,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Panegyrick of gratitude, of which oration <hi>Pamphilus</hi> the Martyr doth (as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> reports) make mention, in his books writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in <hi>Origens</hi> defence.</p>
               <p>Its ſaid of this holy man, that he bleſſed God, when he was Biſhop of <hi>Neocaeſarea</hi> eſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ially for this mercy, that when he firſt undertook that great charge upon him, he found not above ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Chriſtians, and when he left them, he had not in all his juriſdiction ſo many unbelievers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaith of him, that he was ſtiled by the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the truth, another <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Ierom</hi> calls him <hi>virum apoſtolicorum ſignorum &amp; virtutum,</hi> a man of apoſtolical ſignes and vertues, and <hi>Barthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> thus dignifies him too, while he writes him, <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum apoſtolicarum virtutum,</hi> he died (ſay ſome) when <hi>Aurelian</hi> was Emperour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> makes mention of his Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe, which he writ on <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> which <hi>Sui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> calls very ſhort but admirable; this was firſt printed under his own name, but afterwards it came forth under the name of <hi>Gregorie Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zene,</hi> but <hi>Ierome</hi> expounding the fourth chapter of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> and making uſe of this <hi>Gregories</hi> paraphraſe upon ſome paſſage thereof, he doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly diſcover the right Author in theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing words, <hi>vir ſanctus Gregorius Ponti Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:154025:16"/>Originis auditor, in metaphraſi Eccleſiaſtis ita hunc locum intellexit,</hi> A holy man, <hi>Gregory</hi> the Biſhop of Pontus, the auditor of <hi>Origen,</hi> in his metaphraſe of Eccleſiaſtes, thus underſtood this place: the workes of this Father in Greek and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, together with what is now extant of <hi>Macari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> of Egypt and <hi>Baſilius</hi> of Seleucia were printed in one volume at Paris 1622.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Cyprianus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CYprianus</hi> Presbyter of Carthage, being yet a Gentile, was a maſter of Rhetorick, which he publikely profeſſed with great admiration and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, he alſo ſtudied the Magick Art, but being af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards converted to the Chriſtian Faith, he gave that ſtudy over, and applyed himſelf to the ſtudy of the Scriptures: he was ſet over the Churches in Spain, and in the Eaſt, where to his great praiſe he did execute the Office of a labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Biſhop.</p>
               <p>In the writings which this man hath left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, there appear the Symptomes of a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned headpiece, and yet they are not altogether p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re, and free from errour; for he aſſerted that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptizing of Hereticks was neceſſary; this cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion contended with the heathens, and the Jews, as alſo with <hi>Novatus,</hi> and many other hereticks; for which cauſe being grievouſly perſecuted by
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:154025:16"/>his enemies, he ſtept aſide from their fury for the Churches ſake, whoſe peaceand tranquillity his preſence did at that time ſeem to prejudice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Demſter</hi> calls this <hi>Praelat, inſignem authorem, interdum floridum,</hi> a famous Author, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times thetorical and floury: but <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſpeaks more loftily of the man in theſe following words, <hi>Cyprianus Epiſcopus Martyr, unus praecipuns, &amp; cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus extitit, qui &amp; magnam ſibi gloriam ex artis oratoriae profeſſione quaeſivit, &amp; admodum multa conſcripſit in ſuo ſacro genere miranda; erat enim ingenio facili, copioſo, ſuavi, &amp; (quae ſermonis maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma eſt virtus) aperto, ut diſcernere nequeas, utrumne ornatior in eloquendo, an peritior in perſuadendo fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: Cyprian</hi> the Biſhop, and Martyr, was a man very eminent and famous, who acquired to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf great fame and glory by the profeſſion of his Art of Oratory, and he wrote very many things in their ſacred kind admirable, for he was of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil wit, copious, ſweet, and (which is the greateſt vertue of ſpeech) open, that you cannot diſcern whether he were more fluent in ſpeaking, or more skilful in perſwading, <hi>inſtit. lib.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> in his <hi>Bibliotheca</hi> ſpeaking of his phraſe of ſpeech and ſtyle, ſayes this of him <hi>Quod multa piiſſima opuſcula elegantiſſimae phraſeos &amp; Ciceroniano candori proximae ad aedificationem eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae ſcripſit;</hi> that he wrote many moſt pious works of moſt elegant phraſe, and neer <hi>Ciceroes</hi> candour to the edification of the Church, he was an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme charitable man, for as ſoon as he was tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from gentiliſme to chriſtianity, he gave up
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:154025:17"/>all his ſubſtance to the ſupport of poor Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ierome</hi> writing to <hi>Paulinus,</hi> ſaith of this Father, <hi>Quod inſtar fontis puriſſimi levis inceſſit, &amp; placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> that like a moſt pure fountain he ran light and pleaſing: he wrote a famous treatiſe of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, on purpoſe to comfort men againſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching death in the time of a fearful peſtilence. Among all his writings, that treatiſe of his <hi>de uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate eccleſiae,</hi> of the unity of the Church is moſt ſet by and advanced.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in an Epiſtle thus commends this man, <hi>inter Latinos ad apoſtolici pectoris vigorem, ubique ſentias loqui paſtorem, ac martyrio deſtinatum.</hi> And again ſaith he, <hi>In</hi> Cypriano <hi>ſpiritum venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur apoſtolicum,</hi> we reverence in <hi>Cyprian</hi> an apoſtolical ſpirit: t'is <hi>Auſtins</hi> in the ſecond book againſt the <hi>Donatiſts.</hi> chap. 1. <hi>non me terret auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas</hi> Cypriani, <hi>quia reficit humilitas Cypriani</hi> the autority of <hi>Cyprian</hi> doth not terrifie me, becauſe the humility of <hi>Cyprian</hi> doth refreſh me.</p>
               <p>A Deacon of his, by name <hi>Pontius,</hi> wrot the Hiſtory of his life and Martyrdome, he was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyred under <hi>Valerian</hi> and <hi>Galienus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:154025:17"/>
               <head>Arnobius.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ARnobius,</hi> was a famous Rhetorician in <hi>Affrick,</hi> the maſter of <hi>Lactantius,</hi> of whom <hi>Euſebius Pamphilus</hi> reports, that being a teacher of Retho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, and a Gentile, he was conſtrained through ſundry dreames to beleeve the glorious Goſpel, and yet the Chriſtian Biſhops would not receive him to their Fellowſhip, till he had written, and publiſhed thoſe excellent Books of his againſt Gentiliſme; wherein he confuted that vain Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, and Idolatry, whereof he had been before ſo great a Patron, and Advocate? He wrote but ſeven books in number, and the eighth which is thereto added, is none of his compiling, but as ſome ſay, the Author of it, was <hi>Minu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Felix.</hi> He is ſaid, beſides theſe books to have written Commentaries on the Pſalmes; But they are (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> well obſerves) the workes of ſome later Author, which he proves by their making mention of the <hi>Pelagian</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; which was not broached, till the time that <hi>Auſtine</hi> lived, which was many yeers after <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobius;</hi> and beſides <hi>Salmeron</hi> ſpeaks of another Biſhop of the ſame name, to whom he aſcribes thoſe Expoſitions.</p>
               <p>This man flouriſhed about the yeer of Chriſt Chriſt 300. He is not without ſome ſpeciall Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:154025:18"/>
                  <hi>Barthius</hi> ſaith this of him, <hi>Si non exta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, Denſa nox foret in Superſtionibus veterum.</hi> If this man had not been living, it had yet been right in the Superſtitions of the Ancients. <hi>Dempſter</hi> calls him, <hi>virum reconditae eruditionis ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li aſperioris.</hi> A man of deep learning, of rougher ſtile. But <hi>Heniſius</hi> above all others doth advance him; <hi>Ille Patrum praeſul optimus, ille Chriſtianae</hi> Varro <hi>maximus eruditionis.</hi> That preſident of the Fathers, that <hi>Varro</hi> of Chriſtian Erudition, but yet in ſome reſpects <hi>Ierome</hi> doth depreſſe him. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobius inaequalis, &amp; nimius eſt, &amp; abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> operis ſui partitione confuſus. Arnobius</hi> is unequall, and too much, and without partition of his work, confuſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Lactantius Firmianus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LActantius Firmianus,</hi> whom <hi>Alſtedius</hi> ſtiles by the name of <hi>Cicero Chriſtanorum,</hi> the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians <hi>Cicero,</hi> was the Diſciple of <hi>Arnobius,</hi> who being eminent for eloquence in the raign of <hi>Dioccleſian,</hi> taught Rethorick at <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> and and wrote thoſe elegant books againſt the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Heathens, of whom <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaid; <hi>Lact an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, quaſi quidam fluvius eloquentiae</hi> Tullianae, <hi>vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam tam noſtra confirmare potuiſſet, quam facile aliena deſtruxit: Lactantius,</hi> as it were a certain river of Ciceronian Eloquence, I would to God he could as well have confirmed our own, as
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:154025:18"/>he he did deſtroy the Religion of our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lodovicus Vives</hi> having occaſion to mention him, ſaith this of him; <hi>Septem ſcripſit volumina ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantiſſima, &amp; acutiſsima, nec eſt ullus inter Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianos ſcriptores tam vicinus dictioni Tullianae;</hi> He wrote ſeven moſt elegant, and acute volumes, neither doth any among our Chriſtian Writers come ſo neer the ſpeech of <hi>Tully: Piſecius</hi> ſtiles him, <hi>Lacteum, &amp; mellitiſsimum Scriptorem; A milkie and moſt honey writer.</hi> And <hi>Ameſius</hi> too ſpeaking of hm, in his Book entituled, <hi>Bellarmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Enervatus,</hi> thus ſaith: <hi>Quod inter omnes Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres audit Ciceronianus.</hi> That among all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers he is the <hi>Ciceronian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall add but one Elogie more to him, and tis that of <hi>Heniſius. Quid</hi> Tertulliani <hi>porro vim ac lacertos, Quid</hi> Clementis <hi>variam prope incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem ſcientiam, aut</hi> Hilarii <hi>Cothurnum, aut</hi> Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtomi <hi>digreſsiones melle dulciores, aut acumen</hi> Auguſtini, <hi>aut diffuſam &amp; cum ſolo</hi> Cicerone <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferendam</hi> Firmiani <hi>eloquentiam commemorem?</hi> What ſhould I commemorate the force and ſtrength of <hi>Tertullian;</hi> Why the incredible Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of <hi>Clemens,</hi> or the ſtatelineſſe of <hi>Hilary,</hi> or the digreſſions of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> more ſweet then Honey, or the acuteneſſe of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> or the diffuſed eloquence of <hi>Firmianus,</hi> who alone is comparable to <hi>Cicero?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet he is charged by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> with many errours, whoſe words are theſe, <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Sanct. beat. Cap.</hi> 5. <hi>circa fin.</hi> Lactantius <hi>in pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:154025:19"/>errores lapſus eſt, praeſertim circa futurum ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, cum eſſet magis librorum</hi> Ciceronis, <hi>quam Scriptur arum Sanctarum peritus. Lactantius</hi> fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to very many errors, eſpecially about the world to come, ſeeing he was more skilfull in the workes of <hi>Cicero,</hi> then in the books of the holy Scriptures. Hence <hi>Chemnitius</hi> diſcourages us from reading of him, ſaying, <hi>Non multum poteſt juvare Lectorem,</hi> He cannot much profit the reader. <hi>Ierome</hi> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly notes this in him, that he denied the Holy Spirit to be a ſubſtance, or perſon: and beſide this errour, he addes another, whilſt he attributes reaſon to brute creatures. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>inſtit. cap.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>He wrore his book of <hi>Divine Inſtitutions</hi> under <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> as himſelf expreſſeth it in the fourth Chapter of the fifth book; and he pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed it in the Raign of the Great <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> to whoſe Imperiall Majeſty he doth direct his ſpeech in it. He was called <hi>Firmianus</hi> from his Countrey Town <hi>Firmii,</hi> ſituate among the <hi>Picens</hi> in Italy, and <hi>Lactantius,</hi> as one well notes, <hi>a Lacteo eloquentiae flumine,</hi> from his milkie river of Eloquence. He was in his old age Tutour to <hi>Criſpus,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> how he dyed, I read not.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:154025:19"/>
               <head>Euſebius.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EUſebius</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Caeſarea</hi> in <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> he flouriſhed about the yeer of our Lord 320. He was looked on at the firſt, as the principall man of the <hi>Arian</hi> faction. <hi>Chemnitius de lect. Patr.</hi> ſtiles him <hi>apertiſsimum propugnatorem</hi> Arii: A moſt open defender, or abetter of <hi>Arius. Baroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ſtiles him with <hi>Tertullian, manifeſtum Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum;</hi> a manifeſt Heretick. <hi>Ierom</hi> in both his books, which he wrote againſt <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> doth not onely call him <hi>Arianum</hi> an <hi>Arian,</hi> but likewiſe, <hi>ſignife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; principem Arianorum,</hi> The Standard bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, or Enſign of the <hi>Arians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet certainly at the Councill of <hi>Nice</hi> this man brake off his compliance with that Hereticall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and from thence forward joyned himſelf in fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip and ſociety with the Orthodox. Nay, he is conceived by ſome Authors, to have been the compilers of the <hi>Nicene Creed.</hi> He wrote in ten books an Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory, from Chriſts time to the yeer 325. <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith of him, <hi>quod pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre contexuerit Hiſtoriam Eccleſiaſticam. Baſil</hi> calls him <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Worthy of credence, and <hi>Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitius</hi> comparing this authors Hiſtory with that of <hi>Nicephorus,</hi> he ſaith: <hi>Major eſt gravitas in illius hiſtoria, quam in Nicephori.</hi> There is much more gravity in his Hiſtory, then in that of <hi>Nicephorus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:154025:20"/>
               <p>Beſides this work, he writ alſo a <hi>Panagyrick</hi> of the life of Great <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> which comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Acts done in the Church for the ſpace of thirty yeers, together with the Lawes and Edicts that the Emperour had made, relating to the Chriſtian faith. He refuted the Ethnicks and Jewes in his Books of Preparation for, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the Goſpell, he left behinde him a Chronology from <hi>Abrahams</hi> birth to the 326. yeer of our Lord, which doth in all contain 2347. yeers.</p>
               <p>He condemned that peſtilent fellow <hi>Arius</hi> with his own hand in the <hi>Nicene</hi> Councell, and yet further to cleer him from all ſuſpicion of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring that wicked Hereſie and Heretick, <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> hath written an Apology in his behalf, which you will meet in his hiſtory. He died about the yeer of Chriſt, 340. He was called <hi>Pamphilus</hi> from the affection and ſingular love he did bear to <hi>Pamphilus</hi> the Martyr, with whom he was moſt familiar and intimate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bibliander</hi> gives him this Character. <hi>Euſebius, inter Graecos Theologos Anteſignanus. Euſebius</hi> among the Greek Divines the principall. <hi>Cauſabon</hi> calls him <hi>virum longe doctiſsimum, &amp; in omni literarum genere exercitatiſsimum,</hi> A moſt learned man, and moſt exerciſed in all kinde of literature. Tis <hi>Ludovicus Vives</hi> his deſcription of him, <hi>Vir fuit immenſa le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione, &amp; proinde ſumma eruditione.</hi> He was a man of immenſe reading, and for that cauſe of very great erudition.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:154025:20"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scaliger</hi> commends him in one reſpect, and in another diſparages him: as appears by theſe words of his; <hi>Quo</hi> (ſpeaking of this <hi>Euſebius</hi>) <hi>nullus Eccleſiaſticorum veterum plura ad Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am contulit Christianiſmi.</hi> Then whom, none of the Ancient Eccleſiaſtick writers hath contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted more to the Hiſtory of Chriſtianiſme. There is his commendation; <hi>Nullus plura errata in ſcriptis ſuis re liquit, Nullius plures hallucinationes extant.</hi> No man hath left more faults in his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; No man hath extant more errours. There's his diſparagement.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Arrians</hi> having unjuſtly procured the depoſition of <hi>Euſtatius</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Antiochia,</hi> they deſired, that his Office might be ſupplied by this <hi>Euſebius:</hi> but he refuſing it, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſo far commended his modeſty therein, that he ſaid of him, He deſerved to be made Biſhop of the whole world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ierome</hi> obſerving in this mans Commentaries on the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> that he ſwerved from his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and promiſe, whilſt in many places, he imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated <hi>Origens</hi> Allegories; He ſaid this of him; <hi>Ita ſeparata conſociat, ut mirer cum nova ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monis fabrica in unum corpus lapidem, ferum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> conjungere.</hi> He ſo unites things which are ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, that I wonder he doth in his new Fabrick, and Structure of ſpeech joyn together into one body, Stone and Iron.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:154025:21"/>
               <head>Athanaſius.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AThanaſius,</hi> worthy to be immortall in his fame, as his name importeth, was born at Alexandria, and conſecrated Biſhop of that City in the room of <hi>Alexander</hi> deceaſed: this honour was conferred on him in the yeere 325. at which time the Churches of God were moſt grievouſly infeſted, and diſtracted with the Hereſie of <hi>Arius;</hi> ſo that this holy man ſaw he was to ſail in a very ſtormie and tempeſtuous ſea, which made him deſirous at the beginning to decline that high ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement, whereunto he was preferred. His life was not unlike unto a Comedy, his five baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments being fitly reſembled to the five Acts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; the chief cauſe of his troubles (ſay ſome) was <hi>Euſebius</hi> the then Biſhop of <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal member of the Arian faction. For when <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> condemned by the Nicene Council, had made his appeal to great <hi>Conſtantine</hi> with promiſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to diſturb the Churches peace again, and thereupon was licenſed to return unto his charge at Alexandria, where he was a Prieſt; This <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> did refuſe to admit him thereto, and wrote unto the Emperour an account of his refuſal, which was to this effect, <hi>Nempe quod ſemel dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natum haereſeos ab eccleſia, non fas eſſet recipere, abſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que legitima cognitione eccleſiae,</hi> that it was not
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:154025:21"/>lawful to receive an heretick condemned by the cenſure of the Church, without the cognizance of the Church, eſpecially when there appeared no outward ſymptomes of repentance and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from him. Now this reply from <hi>Athanaſius</hi> gave the Emperour great diſcontent, ſo that he moſt ſharply menaced the holy Biſhop, if he did perſiſt in his denial; and now <hi>Euſebius</hi> thinking this opportunity very lucky to his deſigne, he ſo farr improves it, that good <hi>Athanaſius</hi> is moſt ſtrangely traduced, many ſcandalous matters laid unto his charge, as if he impoſed intolerable burdens on the Churches of Egypt, and as though he practiſed treaſon againſt the life of his ſoveraign: but at length being by a Warrant fetcht to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople, he ſo wiped off all theſe foule aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, that he returned with apparent teſtimonies of a ſpotleſs innocence; <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelf diſmiſſing him, not without honour and applauſe.</p>
               <p>But yet his enemies bearing towards him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable malice, and not ſatisfied with this pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like tryal of his Chriſtian ſincerity, do not give over their furious chace, but further accuſe him of other miſdemeanours, as witchcraft, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; but the Judge appointed to hear his cauſe, acquitted him of all thoſe calumnies, and once again the Emperour commends his integrity, and exhorts him to vigilancy in his epiſcopal function.</p>
               <p>But yet at length theſe Arians prevailing, through their importunate ſlanders, procured his exiſe to Trevers in France, where he hid his head for the ſpace of two years and four months,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:154025:22"/>with the Biſhop <hi>Maximinus,</hi> neither did his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings end with the death of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> but his two ſonnes ſwaying the Scepter after him, he was much perſecuted, through the influence his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies had upon <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> of whom they effected that he was three times baniſhed, firſt to <hi>Rome,</hi> then into the remote corners of the eaſt, and laſtly into the deſerts of <hi>Lybia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus indeed was this excellent Prelate toſſed to and fro, finding no reſt for his peaceable feet; no not in thoſe halcyon dayes of the good Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> much leſs in the raign of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> who being alſo removed by death, <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate ſucceeds in the empire, one which at firſt favoured both the perſon and cauſe of <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius,</hi> reſtoring to him his liberty, and attendance on his office; but in the end, he perſecuting the truth, was likewiſe ſtirred up to thunder out a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment againſt him: however God brought him peaceably to his haven in the dayes of the good Emperours <hi>Iovian</hi> and <hi>Valentinian,</hi> who were an <hi>Aſylum</hi> or refuge not to him onely, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to all the perſecuted people of God. This godly Father lived to the ſeventh year of <hi>Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> and then reſted in the Lord, <hi>anno Chriſti.</hi> 371.</p>
               <p>This was a familiar ſpeech of his, <hi>Verberari Chriſtianorum propium eſt, flagellare autem Chriſtianos</hi> Pilati <hi>&amp;</hi> Caiphae <hi>officia ſunt,</hi> Its proper for Chriſtians to be beaten, but to ſcourge them is the office of <hi>Caiphas</hi> &amp; <hi>Pilate:</hi> he was Biſhop of Alexandria forty ſix years, of whoſe moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:154025:22"/>endowments <hi>Gregorie Naziane</hi> is the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter, who ſpeaks thus of him in his funeral orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Athanaſium <hi>laudare idem eſſe, ac virtutem ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam laudare,</hi> to commend <hi>Athanaſius</hi> is to praiſe vertue it ſelf. Indeed no Doctour of the Church ever endured ſo ſharp diſputes, and ſo bitter afflictions for the truth as he.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Photius</hi> the Arch-biſhop of Conſtantinople writing to his brother <hi>Taraſius,</hi> concerning the works of this pious Father, he thus expreſſes him, Athanaſius <hi>in ſermonibus ubique locutione clarus eſt, &amp; brevis, &amp; ſimplex acutus tamen &amp; altus, &amp; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentationibus omnino vehemens, &amp; in his tanta ubertas, ut admirabilis ſit. Athanaſius</hi> in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons is clear in epxreſſion, and ſhort and plain, yet acute and high, in his arguments altogether vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in theſe ſo great fertility, that it is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable. <hi>Theodoret</hi> calls <hi>propugnaculum veritatis,</hi> the fortreſs of truth. Nazianzen, <hi>lumen eccleſiae,</hi> the light of the Church. Epiphaneus, <hi>latrem rectae fidei,</hi> the Father of the Orthodox Faith. Others, <hi>orbis oraculum,</hi> the Oracle of the world. Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> of Wincheſter ſtiles him, <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> the Great; great in many reſpects, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially great for the Creed he compiled.</p>
               <p>His writings againſt <hi>Apollinarius</hi> do excel for grace and ornament, as alſo thoſe Epiſtles of his, wherein he doth excuſe his baniſhment. <hi>Poſſevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> ſaith of him, Athanaſius <hi>fuit tanquam columna eccleſiae adverſus omnes haereticos, Athanaſius</hi> was as as it were the pillar of the Church againſt all hereticks. And another calls him <hi>haeraeticorum
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:154025:23"/>Malleum,</hi> The beetle of Hereticks, as one which knockt them at head by his ſolid and ſubſtantiall reaſonings; When <hi>Iulian</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour had by his Imperiall Edict baniſht him from <hi>Alexandria,</hi> he comforted his people, and friends, whom he found lamenting his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. <hi>Bono animo eſtoto filioli; Nubecula eſt, brevi evaneſcet.</hi> Be of good courage, my ſons, its but a little cloud, and will vaniſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> tells us, That <hi>Gregorie</hi> a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, did ſet forth the life of this Father in an excellent Oration.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Hilarius Pictavienſis.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HIlarius Pictaviencis Epiſcopus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Poict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers,</hi> did ſhine moſt brightly in the Reigns of theſe following Emperours, <hi>Conſtantius, Iuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, Iovinian, Valens,</hi> and <hi>Valentinian.</hi> He was an eloquent Preacher, and a notable Diſputant; he did by his ſolid writings eſtabliſh the diſperſt Churches of <hi>Illyria, France,</hi> and <hi>Italy.</hi> We reade that he was baniſhed with many other Orthodox Biſhops, by the power and Policie of the <hi>Arians,</hi> of whom he was a mighty oppoſer, and Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt; but at length prevailing with the Emperour
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:154025:23"/>
                  <hi>Conſtantius</hi> for his return, he came back to his Charge at <hi>Poictiers</hi> in the yeer 360. Where he found all grievouſly diſtracted, and miſerably af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with the <hi>Arians</hi> leaven; ſo that like a good and skilfull Chirurgion, he laboured to binde up the wounds, and to heal the diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</p>
               <p>He wrote twelve books of the Trinity, wherein, as <hi>Ierom</hi> obſerves, in an Epiſtle of his, <hi>Ad Romanum Oratorem; quod Duodecim</hi> Quintiliani <hi>libros &amp; ſtylo imitatus eſt, &amp; numero.</hi> That he imitated the twelve books of <hi>Quintilian</hi> both in ſtyle, and alſo in number. And in that worke of his he confuted the blaſphemous doctrine of the Hereticke <hi>Arius. Ierome</hi> tells us, that he died in the yeer of Chriſt, 372. when <hi>Valerian</hi> was Emperour: and he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowes on him this worthy Character: <hi>Hillarius Gallicano attollitur cothurno, Eloquentiae Latinae Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danus. Hilary is lifted up with his Gallican buskins, the Rhine of Latine eloquence.</hi> And elſewhere, the ſame Father ſtiles him, <hi>Latinae Sermonis tubam,</hi> The Trumpet of the Latine tongue.</p>
               <p>Some ſay, he wrote on the whole book of Pſalms, which work of his is extant in <hi>Spain:</hi> being a great reader, and ſtudier of <hi>Origen,</hi> he is ſaid to make uſe of <hi>Heliodorus</hi> a Prieſt, who was better skild in the Greek tongue, then himſelf; Hence ſome do impute his miſinterpretation of the Pſalms (whilſt in ſome places he leaves the Grammatical ſenſe, and turns it into one that is Allegoricall, and Anagogicall) meerly to his igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the Hebrew language.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:154025:24"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtus Senenſis,</hi> Speaking of that work of his, and of that on St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> he gives us this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the ſtyle of them; <hi>Stylus abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ulla ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis affectatione preſſus, interdum ſubobſcurus, &amp; ob id a ſimplicium fratrum lectione procul eſt.</hi> His ſtyle ſhort, without any artificiall affectation, ſometimes dark, and obſcure, and for that very reaſon not to be underſtood, or read by unskilfull and illiterate men.</p>
               <p>Tis a commendation which <hi>Eraſmus</hi> gives him. <hi>In</hi> Hilario <hi>grandi materiae parem grandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquentiam, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ut ita dicam, cothurnum admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Biſhop took ſuch great paines to purge the Churches of <hi>France</hi> of the <hi>Arian</hi> Hereſie, and ſo far prevailed by his unwearied labours; that <hi>Ierom</hi> reſembles him to <hi>Deucalion,</hi> who both ſaw the flood of waters overflowing <hi>Theſſalie,</hi> and the abating of them alſo: Even ſo this <hi>Hilarius</hi> ſaw in his time both the growth, and the decay of <hi>Arianiſme</hi> in <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One <hi>Fortunatianus</hi> a ſucceſſour of his, wrote his life in Hexameter verſe, being Biſhop of <hi>Poic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers</hi> in the yeer 570.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:154025:24"/>
               <head>Didymus Alexandrinus</head>
               <p>VVAs an excellent Grammarian, and for his eminency in that Art, was elected Governour of the School of <hi>Alexandria. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> ſo highly extols him in his 65 Epiſtle, that he ſaith there, <hi>Se quod neſcivit, didiciſſe a</hi> Didymo, <hi>quod ſciebat, illo docente, non perdidiſſe.</hi> That he learnt, what he knew not, of <hi>Didymus,</hi> and that he preſerved what he knew, by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. <hi>Nicephorus</hi> doth ſeem to eclipſe him with a report of ſome errours, that he ſhould ſeem to adhere and cleave to: But <hi>Socrates</hi> in his Hiſtory giveth him this credit, That he was a chief Maintainer and Patron of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Faith. And <hi>Zozomene</hi> informs us, <hi>Arianis in Aegypto nihil fuiſſe integri, quamdiu</hi> Didymus <hi>in ea florue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> That <hi>Arius</hi> had no hold at all in <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſo long as <hi>Didymus</hi> flouriſhed there.</p>
               <p>This man was a great acquaintance, and an intimate familiar of <hi>Ieromes,</hi> inſomuch, that that Father was greatly delighted with his ſociety. He tells us this of him, That although he was blinde from his younger dayes, yet he proved an excellent Geometrician, which chiefly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the Inſtrument of ſight, to the wonder of the whole World. He wrote a heavenly Book <hi>de Spiritu Sancto,</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt, which the ſaid <hi>Ierome</hi> tranſlated into the Latine Tongue, and is
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:154025:25"/>now mingled with his Works. He lived to the 83 year of his age, and was almoſt all his time deſirous of privacy and retiredneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith of him, <hi>Se in multis Scripturae lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis difficilibus, eo magiſtro uſum.</hi> That he made uſe of him, to help him out in the explication of many hard Texts of Scripture. And further ſpeaking of his Writings, he gives him this Elogie, <hi>Certe qui hunc legerit latinorum furta cognoſcet, &amp; contemnet rivulos, cum coeperit haurire de fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus; Imperitus Sermone eſt, ſed non Scientia, Apoſtolicum virum ipſo ſtylo exprimens tam ſenſus lumine, quam ſimplicitate verborum.</hi> Truly he that will reade him, will know the thefts of the Latines, and he will deſpiſe the rivulets, when he hath begun to drink of the fountains; he is in Speech unskilful, but not in Science, in his very ſtyle expreſſing an Apoſtolick Author, as well in the light of his ſenſe, as in the ſimplicity of his words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antonius</hi> a Monk, travelling in company with him to the City of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> uſed theſe or the like words to him, (as <hi>Sixtus Sinenſis</hi> delivers them) <hi>Nihil O Didyme turbet te corporalium oculorum jactura, talibus enim deſtitutus es oculis, quibus &amp; Muſcae, &amp; culices videre poſſunt, ſed laetare, quod oculos habes, quibus Angeli vident, &amp; Deus conſideratur, &amp; lux ejus apprehenditur.</hi> Let not the loſs of thy corporal eyes trouble thee, O <hi>Didymus,</hi> for thou art deprived of ſuch eyes, wherewith Flies and Gnats can ſee; but rejoyce thou that thou haſt eyes by which Angels
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:154025:25"/>do behold, and God is conſidered, and his light is apprehended. He flouriſhed under the great <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoſius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Optatus</head>
               <p>BIſhop of <hi>Milevita,</hi> appeared gliſtering in his Orb about the time that <hi>Valentinian</hi> and <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leus</hi> were Emperours. <hi>Morn. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Euchar. cap.</hi> 6. ſaith, that he lived <hi>paulo ante</hi> Auguſtinum <hi>magni in Africa nominis;</hi> a little before <hi>Auguſtine</hi> of great fame in Africa. He was a man well skill'd in moſt kindes of Literature, his life was pious, and his doctrine ſincere and ſound. He ſhewed himſelf a notable <hi>Antidonatiſt,</hi> and thereupon he wrote ſix Books for the confutation of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menianus;</hi> So <hi>Ierome:</hi> But now they are num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred ſeven, the ſeventh conſenting in all reſpects with the ſix, ſo that <hi>Ierome</hi>'s number is concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be erroneous.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Barthius</hi> calls this man <hi>Pium, elegantem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptorem, &amp; quod in eo dignum honore ſummo, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum argumentandi artificem:</hi> A pious, and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant writer, and which is praiſe-worthy, a moſt exquiſite artiſt in arguing and diſputing. <hi>Paraeus</hi> thus expreſſes him, <hi>Vir fuit inſtructus multiplici eruditione, conſtanti pietate &amp; doctrina ſincera.</hi> He was a man well furniſhed with various learning, conſtant piety, and ſound doctrine. Mr. <hi>Leigh</hi> in his Treatiſe of Religion and Learning, calls him
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:154025:26"/>that learned Biſhop of <hi>Milevita.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> of old did aſſert, that the Church of God was no where elſe, but onely among them, limited unto and ſhut up in a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Africk,</hi> where their Hereſie prevailed; this excellent man confuted that opinion by that of the ſecond Pſalm, where God ſaith in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to his bleſſed Meſſias, <hi>Ask of me, and I will give thee the heathen for thine inheritance, and the uttermoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion:</hi> Which Scripture doth evidently demonſtrate the Church of the Goſpel to be ſpred all over the whole world, and not to be reſtrained, as theſe Donatiſts did vainly imagine, to a particular Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p>And whereas they affirmed likewiſe, That the Ordinance of Baptiſm was altogether ineffectual, unleſs ſome of their Miniſters were in place to perform it: He, to confute them, replied, That when God made the world at the beginning, the preſence of the glorious Trinity was powerful enough in operation to create Water, though none of the Donatiſts were then in preſence: Even ſo (ſaith he) the bleſſed Trinity can work effectually in Baptiſm, although not adminiſtred by the Donatiſts; yea, and that it was God, the Author of Baptiſm, and not the Miniſter, which did ſanctifie, a cording as it is expreſſed by the holy man <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 51. <hi>Waſh me, and I ſhall be whiter than ſnow.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:154025:26"/>
               <head>Baſilius Magnus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BAſil</hi> the Great was Biſhop of <hi>Caeſarea</hi> in <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> his father was of the ſame name, and a devout Chriſtian, his brethren were <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> of <hi>Nyſſa,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Sebaſta,</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd to him both for purity of doctrine, and piety of converſation. He was brought up at <hi>Athens,</hi> the School of the Philoſophers, under <hi>Libanius</hi> his Maſter, where he fell into acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with <hi>Gregory Nazianzen.</hi> But after a while leaving <hi>Athens,</hi> he returned to <hi>Caeſarea;</hi> where being called to the Paſtoral Function by the Biſhop of the place <hi>Euſebius,</hi> he expounded ſome places of Scripture with that gravity and accurateneſs, that he was had in great admiration for his abilities and gifts; but at length there ariſing ſome difference betwixt him and <hi>Euſebius,</hi> he diſcreetly withdrew himſelf, on purpoſe to prevent a greater combuſtion.</p>
               <p>However, in the end he was conſtrained to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, through the Faction of the Hereticks, that he might ſtrengthen the hands of the Biſhop a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. But <hi>Euſehius</hi> after a few years de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſing, this <hi>Baſil</hi> was by the general conſent choſen Biſhop in his room. And now he was no ſooner entred on his charge, but he met with many violent and tempeſtuous ſtorms, raiſed by that tyrannous Emperour <hi>Valens</hi> againſt him:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:154025:27"/>For he coming to <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> would have forced this holy man to have cloſed with the doctrine of <hi>Arius,</hi> threatning his refuſal with baniſhment and death. But <hi>Baſil</hi> was moſt reſolute, and coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, as appears by this his gallant anſwer, <hi>Pueris (inquit ille) iſta terriculamenta proponenda eſſe, ſibi vero vitam eripi poſſe, ſed confeſſionem veritatis eripi non poſſe.</hi> Thoſe affrightments (ſaith he) ſhould be propoſed to children: Life indeed might be taken from him, but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the truth could never be taken away from him.</p>
               <p>It is reported, That when he was at his devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Temple, the Emperour coming with his Guard to apprehend and ſeize him, he was himſelf on the ſudden ſurpriſed with ſuch a <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigo</hi> or dizzineſs, that he had faln immediately, if one of his ſervants had not ſupported him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Socrates</hi> tells us in his <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory,</hi> (<hi>Chap.</hi> 21. of thefourth Book) That this Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Son, by name <hi>Galeates,</hi> falling ſick of a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and deſperate diſeaſe, and being given over by Phyſicians, <hi>Dominica</hi> his Mother told her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, that the ſame night ſhe was fearfully diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted with horrible ſhapes, and dreadful viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that the childe was viſited with ſickneſs, becauſe of their ill uſage of <hi>Baſil</hi> the Biſhop. The Emperour well marking the words of his Wife, at length ſent for that good man, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would know the truth, he reaſoned thus with him: If thy Faith (he meant of one ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) be true, pray that my Son die not of this
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:154025:27"/>diſeaſe. Then <hi>Baſil</hi> anſwered, If thou wilt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to believe, as I do, and to bring the Church to Unity and Concord, thy childe without doubt ſhall live. When the Emperour refuſed to yield to this; Let God, ſaith <hi>Baſil,</hi> deal with your ſon as it pleaſeth him: and ſo the childe preſently died.</p>
               <p>This Father lived till the beginning of the reign of the good Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> and was thought to have been the Author of Monaſtical life. The commendations are high, which his friend <hi>Nazianzene</hi> gives him; as who ſtyles him, <hi>Luminare in Mundo, Doctrinae Palatium, &amp; unus Sol inter Syderea:</hi> A Light in the World, a Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of Learning, and as the Sun among the Stars. <hi>Suidas</hi> calls him <hi>Verum celeberrimum, &amp; ad ſummum omnis doctrinae faſtigium progreſſum.</hi> A man moſt famous, that had climbed up to the higheſt ſtep of all Learning. <hi>Cauſſinus</hi> ſaith, That <hi>Libanius,</hi> though his Maſter, did prefer him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all other Authors: <hi>Erat illi unus pro centum millibus in eloquentia Baſilius.</hi> And this ſayes <hi>Eraſmus</hi> alſo of him, <hi>Baſilius, dilucidus, pius, ſanus, ſuaviter, gravis, &amp; graviter ſuavis, nihil habens affectate loquacitatis. Baſil</hi> is clear, pious, ſound, ſweetly grave, and gravely ſweet, having nothing in him of affected loquacity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:154025:28"/>
               <head>Gregorius Nyſſenus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GRegorius Nyſſenus,</hi> Brother to <hi>Baſil</hi> the Great, called <hi>Nyſſen</hi> from the Church of <hi>Nyſſa,</hi> whereof he was Biſhop, but when he was conſecrated, it is not with any certainty reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. He joyned with his Brother <hi>Baſil,</hi> and <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory Nazianzen,</hi> againſt the <hi>Arians,</hi> whom both with their word and pen they notably confuted. Neither was this Father more backward and ſlack in oppoſing the Hereſie of <hi>Eunomius:</hi> and if we will take the word of Reverend <hi>Theodoret,</hi> this Doctor ever ſhewed himſelf zealous in with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that, whatever it was, which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the rule and power of godlineſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicephorus</hi> tells us, in his 12 Book, and 13 Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, That in the General Council of <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> this man did ſupply that, which was lacking in the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, this clauſe being by him added, <hi>And in the Holy Ghoſt, the Lord and giver of life, who proceedeth from the Father and the Son, who with the Father and the Son together is worſhipped and glorified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Suidas</hi> doth beſtow upon him theſe two Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters: <hi>Gregorius Nyſſenus, omni doctrina refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, in multum profecit, &amp; illuſtris evaſit, ut quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam veterum. Gregory Nyſſen</hi> being ſtuft full with all Learning, profited ſo much therein, that he was judged as famous as any of the Ancients.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:154025:28"/>And again the ſame Author calls him, <hi>Eloquentiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum, &amp; multiplici eruditione praeſtantem:</hi> Moſt eloquent, and excelling in variety of Learning.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Cauſſinus</hi> gives him this following Elogie, <hi>Quid</hi> Gregorius Nyſſenus, <hi>&amp;</hi> Caeſarius? <hi>Num ipſi</hi> Gregoriorum <hi>fato aureum flumen orationis fundunt?</hi> This mans Brother <hi>Baſil,</hi> being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by untimely death from finiſhing his Commentaries on the ſix dayes works, <hi>Socrates</hi> tells us, That this <hi>Gregory</hi> compleated them, and made them perfect.</p>
               <p>Theſe were the eminent and remarkable ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of this Father: He ſaid concerning Sin, <hi>That although the Serpents which ſtung us were not here ſlain outright, yet their venemous ſtings could not mortally wound us.</hi> And concerning Pilgrimage, he ſaid, <hi>That a Pilgrimage from the Luſts of the Fleſh to the Righteouſneſs of God, and the Sanctification of the heart, was onely accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to God, and not a journeying from</hi> Cappado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia <hi>to</hi> Paleſtina; <hi>and that God would give a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the world to come, onely to things done in this world by the warrant of his own Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Leo</hi> the Emperour called this Father <hi>Dulcem &amp; illuſtrem Eccleſiae fontem,</hi> The ſweet and illuſtrious fountain of the Church. He was elder Brother to <hi>Baſil,</hi> but died after him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:154025:29"/>
               <head>Gregorius Nazianzenus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GRegorius Nazianzenus,</hi> was born at <hi>Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zum,</hi> a town neer to <hi>Ceſarea</hi> in <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> where <hi>Baſil</hi> the Great was Biſhop, who out of a deſire he had to learning, went to <hi>Athens,</hi> to imploy his time there in the ſtudy of the Arts; whence returning home, he was Baptized about the twentieth yeer of his age, and after that giving himſelf up to the ſtudy of the Chriſtian Religion, he was at length urged by his father to take upon him the Miniſtery, and to aſſiſt him being then aged in the execution of his paſtorall charge.</p>
               <p>Yet his parents after a while deceaſing, he left his Countrey for ſome yeers, and lived private; but comming afterwards to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> he preached in the Church of <hi>Anaſtaſia,</hi> all the other Oratories of the City being taken up, and filled by the <hi>Arians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here is one thing to be noted, that though ſo eminently learned and pious a man, as was this <hi>Nazianzene,</hi> was then preſent, yet the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councill held there at that time, preferred one <hi>Nectarius,</hi> a Noble man of <hi>Cilicia</hi> to the Biſhoprick of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> before him: a man which was at that time but a <hi>Catechumenus,</hi> and never before advanced to any <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:154025:29"/>overpaſſing this great Doctour, and overlooking this great light.</p>
               <p>And here it was, that he fell into controverſie with <hi>Apollinarius</hi> the Heretick, who was ſo impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, as to accuſe <hi>Nazianzene</hi> of ſedition before the Magiſtrate, but the Biſhop did very fairly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit himſelf of the crime. It is ſaid of this grave and holy man, <hi>quod ſolus poſt</hi> Johannem Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſtam, <hi>Theologi nomen meruit.</hi> That he onely after <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> merited the eminent title of <hi>Divine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There happening diſſentions amongſt his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Biſhops, he withdrew himſelf for retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his Fathers Countrey Farme houſe, as being weary of all publike congreſſions, whereof he ſeldom ſaw any profitable iſſue, by reaſon of the ambition of the diſputants.</p>
               <p>He lived all his life time unmarried, and dyed not under the 90th. yeer of his age, in the yeer of Chriſt 384. he wrote much againſt thoſe Hereticks, which either did impugne the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, or Humanity of our Lord, and he was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe moſt vigorouſly active againſt the Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme of the Gentiles in thoſe two invectives of his, wherein he chaſtiſeth that Apoſtate <hi>Iuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> who would needs be a reſtorer of Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ierom</hi> owns this holy Father for his Maſter, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> quo Scripturas explanante didicit;</hi> From <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>om, as his interpreter, he learn't the Scriptures. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s this learned man did admire <hi>Baſil,</hi> ſo did <hi>Baſil</hi> him, as appears by this Elogie he gives
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:154025:30"/>him. <hi>Vas electionis, &amp; puteus profundus os Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti</hi> Gregorius. Now for this mans ſpeech, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med (as <hi>Suidas</hi> ſaith) to come neer to <hi>Polemons,</hi> or to <hi>Iſocrates,</hi> ſo ſaies <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> as alſo it was not unlike to <hi>Ambroſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſpeaking of his piety, he tells us, that it did <hi>ex aequo propemodum certare cum facundia;</hi> It was even as eminent, and illuſtrious as his eloquence; and the commendation which <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> gives him, is, <hi>quod ſapientiam mirificie eum eloquentia copulavit.</hi> That he marvellouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly coupled his wiſdom with his eloquence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Epiphanius.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EPiphanius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salamine</hi> in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> was inſtructed in learning by certain Monkes in <hi>Egypt,</hi> from whence he went into <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving there a Monaſticall life, and improving his time in the ſtudy of Philoſophy, ſo that in few yeers his proficiency therein was mightily increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and advanced.</p>
               <p>He wrote a book in confutation of no leſſe then 80. Hereſies, which is called his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, wherein is alſo comprehended, a Hiſtory from Chriſt even to his own times. He flouriſhed in the reigns of the Emperours <hi>Valens,</hi> and <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian,</hi> being Contemporary with thoſe grand Lights of the Church, <hi>Baſil</hi> the Great, <hi>Gregory
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:154025:30"/>Nazianzene, Iohn Chryſoſtome,</hi> with the latter of which, he had a ſharp contention about the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of <hi>Origen,</hi> which <hi>Epiphanius</hi> would have condemned as Hereticall at the Synod of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople,</hi> but <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> withſtood it: in which bickering of theirs, this hapned worthy of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration; That one was a true Prophet to the other: <hi>Epiphanius</hi> preſaging the depoſition of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> the ſudden death of <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> both which were accordingly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed; the one being afterwards depoſed, and the other dying in his return to <hi>Cyprus. Suidas</hi> ſaith thus much of this mans works: <hi>Quod a doctis ob res, ab indoctis propter verba le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur:</hi> and <hi>Ierom</hi> ſaid the like. That they are read of the learned for their matter, and of the unlearned for their words.</p>
               <p>His <hi>Panarium</hi> is ſtiled by another, <hi>Vniverſae antiquitatis Eccleſiaſticae promptuarium,</hi> A Cellar, or Storehouſe of all Eccleſiaſticall Antiquity. He was maſter of five learned tongues, and thence it was that <hi>Ierom</hi> honoured him with this Epithet, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> addes this Elogie, <hi>Apud Graecos inter magnos habitus, &amp; a multis in Catholicae fidei ſanitate laudatus.</hi> With the Greeks he was reputed among the great ones, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by many for his ſoundneſs in the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Faith.</p>
               <p>And yet <hi>Druſius</hi> faſtens many an errour on him. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>obſervat. cap.</hi> 21. Epiphanium <hi>ſcimus omnes in multis graviter hallucinatum.</hi> We all
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:154025:31"/>know that <hi>Epiphanius</hi> grievouſly erred in many things.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Ambroſius Mediolanenſis.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AMbroſius Mediolanenſis Epiſcopus,</hi> the Biſhop of Millain, being Leiutenant of the Province, was choſen Biſhop of the City by the unanimous conſent of the people, and therein confirmed by the Emperour <hi>Valentinian;</hi> he was high in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of five moſt noble Princes, <hi>Valentinian</hi> the elder, <hi>Gratian, Valentinian</hi> the younger, <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> the great, and <hi>Honorius:</hi> he was a man of great fame amongſt the eaſtern Churches, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry intimate and familiar with <hi>Baſil</hi> of Caeſarea, and other eminent and famous Doctors, even as the inſcriptions of his Epiſtles to diverſe of them, do inſinuate.</p>
               <p>He baptized <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and was likewiſe his maſter: before he was Biſhop of Millain, he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned Liguria, he wrote many excellent books, which deſerved thoſe characters that the learned have given him. <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſaith thus of him, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſius <hi>juxta nomen ſuum vere coeleſti manat Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſia, dignus quiſit, quod dicitur Ambroſius, hoc eſt immortalis, non ſolum apud Chriſtum, ſed etiam apud homines. Ambroſe</hi> according to his name doth truely flow with heavenly <hi>Ambroſia,</hi> who is worthy to be what he is called, <hi>Ambroſius,</hi> that is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:154025:31"/>immortal, not with Chriſt onely, but with men alſo.</p>
               <p>Its <hi>Auguſtines</hi> commendation of him, <hi>ejus elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quià ſtrenue miniſtrant adipem frumenti divini, &amp; laetitiam olei, &amp; ſobriam vini ebrietatem,</hi> his elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent ſpeeches do ſtoutly adminiſter the fat of divine bread-corn, and the joy of oyle, and of wine a ſober drunkenneſs; one of the Latine Poets ſpeaks his worth in this following diſtich.
<q>
                     <l>Cedite doctores Romani, cedite graii</l>
                     <l>Neſcio quid majus naſcitur <hi>Ambroſio!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperour being ſuſpended from the Sacrament by this excellent Prelate, becauſe he came to it with the guilt of bloud upon his ſoul, (for being angry with the inhabitants of Theſſalonica, he had cauſed ſeven thouſand of them to be ſlain, having drawn them together for that end to a Stage-play) he ſaid of this <hi>Ambroſe, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem ſe noſſe, qui vere ſciret epiſcopum gerere, praeter unum</hi> Ambroſium, that he did not know any man, that truely knew how to behave himſelf like a Biſhop, beſides <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> He dyed in the year of the Lord 398. aged 64 years.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Hieronymus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HIeronymus</hi> was brought up at Rome in the time of Pope <hi>Damaſus,</hi> &amp; flouriſhed in the Church about the year of Chriſt 390. providence
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:154025:32"/>ſo ordering, that there ſhould ariſe ſuch ſhining lights at that time when the Church was peſtered with the hereſies of <hi>Arius</hi> and <hi>Pelagius,</hi> there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no leſs then ten or twelve, which in that ſhort tract of time preſented themſelves to oppoſe them, among which this Father was one of the chiefeſt.</p>
               <p>He was a great traveller, and had compaſſed the greateſt part of Europe, that he might have confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with the learned of that age; at length retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to Judea, he ſeated himſelf about Bethlehem, where he compoſed moſt of thoſe works we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy at this day, and there he dyed full of dayes, in the yeer of Chriſt 416. and in the 12 of the raign of <hi>Honorius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The learned of latter times have highly extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his repute and fame. Hieronymus <hi>blandum facundiae nomen, &amp; ſummis in omnibus artifex,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cauſſinus, Ierom</hi> a pleaſant name of eloquence, and in all things the beſt artiſt: <hi>Barthius</hi> gives him this Elogy, Hieronymi <hi>ingenium hoc fuit, ut conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſibi profundiſſimae eruditionis paucis dicere plura, &amp; ſalem quendam acuminis relinquere velit in ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo legentis;</hi> this was <hi>Ieroms</hi> wit, that being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to himſelf of his deep learning, he would ſpeak much in few words, and leave a reliſh of his ingenuity in the mind of the Reader. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is very ſpa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of ſpeaking in his praiſe, becauſe he lived in his time, and was his ſcholar.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Heniſius</hi> doth of late break out into admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of him, <hi>Quo tandem modo, aut quibus ego verbis (tuam maxime</hi> Hieronyme) <hi>ingentem ſimul
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:154025:32"/>pietatem ac facundiam deſcribam!</hi> After what manner and with what words (O moſt great <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi>) ſhall I deſcribe thy vaſt piety and eloquence; how ſhall I expreſs and declare thy skill, which was ſo admirable in all tongues, and in all anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and Philoſophy; this <hi>Heniſius</hi> ſpeaks, and much more of him in one of his orations: they write that this man of all the Fathers onely had knowledge of the Hebrew tongue.</p>
               <p>When he was at Rome he grew into acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with ſome of the honourable Ladies there, as <hi>Marcella, Sophronia Principia, Paula,</hi> and <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtochium,</hi> to whom he opened many difficult and knotty texts of Scripture, for he was then a Prieſt: after he left Rome, as he journied to Paleſtine, he acquainted himſelf with thoſe three Doctors, <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius</hi> Biſhop of Cyprus, <hi>Nazianzene</hi> and <hi>Dydi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> yet he was more addicted to an Eremetical life then to ſociety.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in his Preface to <hi>Hilarius,</hi> having made mention of this Father, he ſubjoynes this teſtimony, <hi>quo viro nihil habet orbis latinius, &amp; doctius vel ſanctius,</hi> then which man, the world hath nothing more Latin, and more learned, or more holy; <hi>Auſtin</hi> alſo ſpeaking of his elegant ſpeech, ſaith thus, <hi>cujus eloquium ex oriente in oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidente inſtar lampadis reſplenduit,</hi> whoſe elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, like a Lamp, did ſhine out of the eaſt into the weſt.</p>
               <p>Yet this Father was not altogether free from errours. Concerning the worlds creation, it was his opinion, that the Angels thoſe ſpiritual crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:154025:33"/>were made long before the viſible world, and where he writes againſt <hi>Iovinian,</hi> he doth not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain ſo honourable thoughts of marriage as doth become him, for he ſeems there to diſlike of ſecond marriage, which the Apoſtle alloweth of, becauſe the bed is undefiled, and alſo an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient againſt unlawful burning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Aurelius Auguſtinus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AUrelius Auguſtinus,</hi> the moſt doctrinall in his writings of all the Ancient Worthies, was an <hi>Affrican</hi> by birth, whereupon the learned Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> calls him, <hi>Decus Africae,</hi> The glory of <hi>Africa.</hi> He is not to be accounted as the laſt of the pious Fathers; who having been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in Rhetorick at <hi>Carthage,</hi> was at the beginning a complier with the <hi>Manachees.</hi> His life for the greater part of it, is written by his own pen in his confeſſions. Afterwards being bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> he returned into the right way, and ſucceeded <hi>Valerius</hi> in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po,</hi> about the yeer of Chriſt, 390.</p>
               <p>The coverſion of this man was in this manner. Having read the life of <hi>Antonius</hi> the <hi>Eremite,</hi> as well as heard the Sermons of <hi>Ambroſius,</hi> and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:154025:33"/>being therewith wonderfully moved, and affected, he began to diſreliſh his former converſation, which he had waſted in the vanities and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of ſin, and going into a Garden with his friend <hi>Alipius,</hi> there he fell to bemoan with tears the abominations of his youthfull dayes, wiſhing the time now at hand, that his ſoul ſhould be watered with true converting grace: And as his heart was thus melting into penitentiall ſorrows, he heard a voice ſay to him, <hi>Tolle &amp; lege,</hi> Take up the book, and read; and again, <hi>Tolle &amp; lege,</hi> Take up the book, and read, for he had his Bible in the Garden with him, and ſeeing no body there, he then perceived, it was an admonition and a word to him from Heaven, whereupon he open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the book, and the firſt place he lighted on, was <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.13, 14. <hi>Not in gluttony and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not in chambering and wantonneſſe, not in ſtrife and envying, but put ye on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> At the reading whereof, he was ſo far tranſported, that he reſolved to become a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, and ſo to live, as to ſhew forth the fruits of a good reformation.</p>
               <p>He maintained Diſputations with very many Hereticks, as the <hi>Arians,</hi> the <hi>Manichees,</hi> the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts,</hi> and the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> whoſe unſound de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices he gravely confuted, and ſo ſtood up for the defence of the Chriſtian Truth, as if he on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of all men were called to that employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>When the city of <hi>Hippo</hi> was ſtraightly beſieged by the <hi>Vandals,</hi> he was therein encloſed, but yet
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:154025:34"/>dyed peaceably before it was taken, in the third moneth of the ſiege, and in the yeer of Chriſt 433. being aged 76. yeers. I ſhall not let him paſſe without his deſerved Encomiums. <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſpeaks thus of him; <hi>Eximius Pater inter ſumma Eccleſiae ornamenta, ac lumina Princeps.</hi> An excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Father, amongſt the great Ornaments and Lights of the Church the chief. And thus doth alſo <hi>Sariſber: Doctor ille Eccleſiae, cujus nemo ſatis memor eſſe poteſt.</hi> That Doctour of the Church, of whom no man can be enough mindfull.</p>
               <p>And not to omit that of <hi>Ludovicus Vives, Fuit in illo vira ſtudium uberrimum, cognitio Scriptura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Sacrarum exactiſſima, Iudicium acre, ac ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſum, Ingenium ad miraculum arctum.</hi> He is ſo deep in ſome of his works, that <hi>Ierome</hi> in one of his Epiſtles doth not ſtick to call him the moſt obſcure Expoſitour of the Scripture. Yet this man, that he might deſcend to the capacities of the unskilfull, and rude multitude, he would frequently ſpeak Barbariſmes, having this expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion often in his mouth, <hi>Malo ut me reprehendant Grammatici, quam ut non intelligant populi,</hi> I had rather Grammatians ſhould reprehend me, then the people ſhould not underſtand me.</p>
               <p>Our learned <hi>Whitaker</hi> ſpeaking of him, ſaith, <hi>quod magnum eſt ejus in Eccleſia nomen.</hi> That his name is great in the Church. There is one thing which he himſelf would have all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to obſerve in his works, Tis the fourfold diſtinction of Time, wherein they were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Some of them he wrote when he was
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:154025:34"/>Catechumenus, and ſo are inflated, and puft up with with ſecular learning. Others, when he was but newly baptized, and but a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the ſtudy of Theologie: others, when he was Preſbyter, and therefore more exact then the former; and laſtly, others, when he was choſen Biſhop, and ſo moſt elaborate and excellent of them all. Theſe diſtinctions of Time would this Father have every reader take notice of, that they might thence ſee his proficiency in Sacred learning, and thereby might be the more eaſily induced to excuſe him, ſeeing he makes amends in his latter works, for the imperfections of his former ones.</p>
               <p>Of all his works, his Retractations and Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions do bring moſt honour to him, the one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a meek acknowledgement of his Errors, or Lapſes of judgement, the other a confeſſion of his Falls, or Lapſes of his life.</p>
               <p>Of all his Commentaries on the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, thoſe which be hath written upon the Pſalms are moſt diſliked, whereupon one of the learned ſaith of him, <hi>nunquam infelicius in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis Sanctis verſatus, quam in pſalmorum enar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:154025:35"/>
               <head>Cyrillus Alexandrinus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CYrillus Alexandrinus,</hi> ſo called, becauſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Alexandria, and in diſtinction to another of the ſame name, Biſhop of <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> He flouriſhed about the year of Chriſt 433. in the reign of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the younger. There was great ſtrife and contention about chooſing of this man Biſhop; ſome were for one <hi>Timotheus,</hi> and the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>incipal man or head of that party was <hi>Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datius,</hi> the Captain of the Garriſon, who labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed might and main to croſs the choice of this <hi>Cyrillus,</hi> and to further the election of <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet notwithſtanding all oppoſition, <hi>Cyrils</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty prevailed, and carried it; who being inveſted with his Epiſcopal Juriſdiction, did take more ſtate upon him, than any of his Predeceſſors ever did before him: For there hapning a combuſtion betwixt the Jews and the Chriſtians in that City, this <hi>Cyril</hi> would not ſtoop ſo low, as to make his complaint to <hi>Oreſtes</hi> the chief Governour, and to crave juſtice of him againſt the wrong doers, but uſurping to himſelf the Office of a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, he ſet upon thoſe Jews, and ſpoiled them of all their goods, which cauſed a great breach betwixt the Deputy and the Biſhop, inſomuch that five hundred Monks of <hi>Nitria</hi> came out of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:154025:35"/>the Wilderneſs, to ſide with <hi>Cyril</hi> their Prelate; and one of them, by name <hi>Ammonius,</hi> wounding the Governour in the ſcuffle, was thereupon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, and forthwith condemned and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted: whom <hi>Cyrillus</hi> enrolled for a Martyr, and changing his name, called him thenceforth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, <hi>Wonderful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He contended againſt <hi>Neſtorius</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> whom the Council of <hi>Epheſus</hi> had condemned for an Heretick. He refuted the Errours of the Arians and Eunomians. He died in the year of our Lord 444. after he had ſate in the Chair of Alexandria 32 years.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicephorus</hi> tells us, That this <hi>Cyrillus</hi> did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe an hoſtile hatred againſt <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> for no other cauſe, but becauſe he did diſſent in his judgement from the opinion of his Uncle <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus. Niceph. lib.</hi> 14. <hi>cap.</hi> 27. <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> calls him, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The Seal of the Faith of the Fathers. Leo</hi> the Emperour equals him to <hi>Athanaſius, Baſil, Nazianzen, Nyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> for eminency of exploits, as their fellow, <hi>Conſtit.</hi> 88. <hi>Nicephorus</hi> in his 14 Book and 14 Chapter, ſpeaks thus of him, <hi>Ad certamina natum, nullam prorſus haereſin graſſari paſſum fuiſſe.</hi> That being born for conflicts and debates, he would not ſuffer any hereſie to ſpred. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> affords him this Elogie, <hi>Cyrillus vir fuit ſanctiſſimus, &amp; doctiſſimus, at praeſertim circa myſterium incarnationis Dominica a Deo doctus. Bell. de Script. Eccl. pag.</hi> 210. <hi>Cyril</hi> was a moſt holy and moſt learned man, but taught of God
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:154025:36"/>eſpecially about the Myſtery of our Lords Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Johannes Chryſoſtomus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IOhannes Chryſoſtomus,</hi> whom <hi>Montacutius</hi> calls <hi>Patrum diſertiſſimum, &amp; in Scripturis enarran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis Graecorum principem,</hi> The moſt eloquent of the Fathers, and in the unfolding the Scriptures, of the Greeks the chief, was born at Antioch of a Noble Family, his Parents names were <hi>Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> and <hi>Anthuſa;</hi> ſo <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> tells us. He learnt Rhetorick of <hi>Libanius,</hi> and Philoſophy of <hi>Andragathius,</hi> and Theologie of <hi>Diodorus</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Tarſus.</hi> He was a great admirer of <hi>Ariſtophanes,</hi> whoſe Comedies he would uſually put under his Pillow; whence, ſome ſay, he ſuckt his admirable eloquence.</p>
               <p>He made ſo great progreſs in his Studies, that he was the wonder of all that heard him. After he was baptized, he altogether ſpent his time in ſearching the hidden ſenſe of the Scriptures, and firſt he was appointed Lecturer at <hi>Antioch,</hi> and laſt of all Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> having with that many Churches of <hi>Thrace, Aſia</hi> and <hi>Pontus</hi> committed to his juriſdiction.</p>
               <p>He uſed great freedom of ſpeech, as one that would neither ſeek the favour, nor dread the power of any. He was much envied and hated
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:154025:36"/>by the falſe Brethren, who made it their work to load this zealous man with ſlanders and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, eſpecially <hi>Theophilus</hi> the Alexandrian Biſhop, who was indeed the cauſe of the diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwixt him and <hi>Epiphanius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was likewiſe perſecuted by the Empreſſe <hi>Eudoxia,</hi> which prevailed with her husband for his baniſhment; but being recall'd again by <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadius,</hi> when it was expected he ſhould become much more ſparing, and leſs bitter in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, he perſiſted ſtill in his reproving of the Empreſs; whereat her husband much incenſed, exiled him again to <hi>Pontus,</hi> where being ſurpriſed with an head-ache, and falling ill of a Feaver, he concluded his life in the year of Chriſt 407.</p>
               <p>The Elogies of this Father are tranſcendent. <hi>Suidas</hi> thus applauds him, <hi>Lingua ejus Nili ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taractis uberior, nemo certa ab omni aevo tanta di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendi copia affluxit quanta ſolus ille abundavit; &amp; ſolus abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fuco aureum &amp; divinum illud nomen eſt conſecutus. Numerum ſcriptorum ejus recenſere, non eſt hominis, ſed Dei potius, omnia ſcientis.</hi> His tongue more plentifull than the ſluces of <hi>Nilus;</hi> never did any in all ages flow with ſo great a ſtream of eloquence, as he alone hath abounded; and he onely hath without falſhood obtained that golden and divine Name. To reckon up all his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, it is not in the reach of man, but rather of God, who knoweth all things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cauſſinus</hi> ſtyles him, <hi>Theatrum quoddam divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae eloquentiae, in quo Deus abunde videri voluit, quid poſſit vitae ſanctitas cum vi dicendi conjuncta:</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:154025:37"/>A certain Theatre of divine eloquence, in whom God would abundantly manifeſt, what ſanctity of life was able to effect, being joyned with the fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e of clocution. Another allows him this Epithet, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Golden-word Chryſoſtome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theoderet</hi> in <hi>Photius</hi> his <hi>Bibliotheca,</hi> thus ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vates this man, <hi>O egregium poſt mortem ducem! O Triſtem etiam hoſtibus poſt ſepulturam mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem! O Lyram omni harmonia praeditam morte jam ſolutam! O Theatrum tanto Tibicine or ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp;c.</hi> O egregious Captain after death! O Souldier, ſorrowful to thy enemies after burial! O Harp, endued with all harmony, now broken by death! O Theatre, deprived of ſo great a Minſtrel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> ſpeaking in the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Tongue, he tells us, That <hi>Libanius</hi> himſelf, the Maſter of this <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly admire the fluency and grace thereof; and to that purpoſe he preſents us with a ſhor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Epiſtle written to him by <hi>Libanius,</hi> wherein he highly extolleth his Attick eloquence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Leo Primus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LEo Primus</hi> was by Nation an Italian, born <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Thuſcany,</hi> and choſen Pope about the 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> year of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> and the 16 of <hi>Valentinian</hi> He ſate in the Chair near 21 years. He procure
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:154025:37"/>a Council to be called by the Emperour <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> againſt the Hereſie of <hi>Eutyches,</hi> which had in that age ſpread it ſelf, and infected the Church of God: but yet it ſo fell out by the ſubtilty of <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> the preſent Biſhop of Alexandria, that this foul errour was rather ſtrengthned in that Council, than weakned, and rather ratified, than ſuppreſſed.</p>
               <p>Among this mans Canons, and Papal Decrees, none is more worthy of praiſe, than his Edict againſt ſelf-ſeeking ambitious men, who affect continually ſuperiorities &amp; advancements. He or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that ſuch ſhould be deprived of all maner of dignities and preferments, as well Offices of lower degree, as higher and more ſublime; of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour ones for their pride, becauſe they had ſo ſcornfully deſpiſed them; and of the higher ones for their preſumption and ambition, becauſe they had ſo greedily affected them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> ſtyles this man, <hi>In divinis Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturis eruditiſſimum, &amp; in declamandis homiliis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundiſſimum,</hi> Moſt learned in the Scriptures, and moſt eloquent in his Homilies. He wrote many Epiſtles, ſome to the Emperours, others to Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, others to the Churches of divers Provinces; but of them all, that Epiſtle which he wrote to <hi>Flavianus</hi> Biſhop of Conſtantinople, wherein he impugned the blaſphemous opinion of the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick <hi>Eutyches,</hi> is preferred for its ſingular ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pareus</hi> ſpeaking of his writings, ſaith thus of them, <hi>In ſcriptis ejus elucet ſumma vis Ingenii,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:154025:38"/>&amp; mira in repellendis haereticorum ictibus dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas:</hi> There ſparkleth in his writings a notable vigour of wit, and a wonderful dexterity in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling the ſtrokes of Hereticks. He laboured (as many of his Predeceſſors had done before him) for the Primacy of the Roman Chair, but with much more craft and cunning; whence <hi>Chamierus</hi> gives him this ſuitable character, <hi>Leo Magnus primus fuit Epiſcopus Romanus, &amp; qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ambitioſiſſimus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>Attilus</hi> King of the <hi>Hunnes</hi> fell in upon <hi>Italy,</hi> and waſted moſt part of it, and was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching with his bloody Army to <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, with a full purpoſe to deſtroy it, this man with one of the Conſuls, and part of the Senate, wen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> forth to meet him; and ſo far he prevailed by his inſinuating Rhetorick, that he perſwaded him to ſpare the City, beyond the expectation of all men.</p>
               <p>And after this, when <hi>Genſericus,</hi> that Tyrant of the <hi>Vandals,</hi> and great perſecuter of ſuch as were ſound in the Faith, came with his diſplayed Banners againſt <hi>Rome,</hi> being wooed thither by <hi>Eudoxia,</hi> to revenge the death of her ſlain huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band <hi>Valentinian</hi> the late Emperour; he ſo wrought upon him by his conquering eloquence, that he was content onely with the ſpoils and plunder of the City, altogether abſtaining from ſlaughter and bloodſhed.</p>
               <p>No marvel then, if <hi>Trithemius</hi> ſtyle this Pope, <hi>Primum Eccleſiaſticae dictionis</hi> Tullium, <hi>ſacra Theologiae</hi> Homerum, <hi>Rationum fidei</hi> Ariſtotelem,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:154025:38"/>
                  <hi>Autoritatis Apoſtolicae Petrum, &amp; in Criſtiane pulpite Paulum.</hi> The firſt <hi>Tully</hi> of Eccleſiaſtick ſpeech, The <hi>Homer</hi> of Sacred Theologie, the <hi>Ariſtole</hi> of Reaſons of Faith, the <hi>Peter</hi> of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall Authority, and the <hi>Paul</hi> in a Chriſtian pulpit.</p>
               <p>In this mans time thoſe horrible earthquakes were aſſwaged, which had ruined ſo many emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Towns and cities. The Papiſts do attribute ſome miracles to him, as they have done to ſome other Popes before him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Theodoretus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THeodoretus,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Cyrus</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> was the Scholar of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> of whom he was inſtructed both in Philoſophy, and Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie: he wrote an Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory, compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing the beginnings of the <hi>Arian</hi> Sect, and the contentions of the Church, from the firſt yeer of Great <hi>Conſtantine</hi> to the beginning of the Raign of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> which in all contains the ſpace of an hundred and five yeers.</p>
               <p>He had conflicts with the Heretick <hi>Eutyches,</hi> not onely with voice, but with ſtyle alſo. It's reported that his Mother being aged, and as it were paſt hopes of having a childe, the Monkes of <hi>Syria</hi> prevailed by their prayers for his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, who, as ſoon as he was borne, was forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with conſecrated to God; <hi>Cauſsinus</hi> joyning him with <hi>Clemens</hi> and <hi>Cyrillus,</hi> thus ſpeaketh of him
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:154025:39"/>
                  <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus, Cyrillus &amp; Theodoretus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eloquentes ſumme docti, inter doctos ſumme elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentes.</hi> Amongſt the Eloquent wonderouſly Learned, amongſt the Learned wonderonſly elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent.</p>
               <p>This man was Anathematized by <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and unjuſtly depoſed from his Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick, becauſe he conſented with <hi>Flavianus</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in the condemnation of the <hi>Euti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chian</hi> Hereſie; he is ſaid to have written a depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory letter to Pope <hi>Leo</hi> for his reſtitution unto his Epiſcopal juriſdiction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dalleus</hi> ſtiles him, <hi>virum ſui ſeculi eruditiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum;</hi> The moſt learned man of the age he lived in. <hi>Illyrius</hi> ſayes of him, <hi>Quod inſtructus Ingenio excellentiſſimo, &amp; ad omnis generis diſciplinas perci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piendas capaciſſimo fuit,</hi> that he was furniſhed with a moſt excellent wit, and moſt capable of all manner of learnings.</p>
               <p>He was <hi>Cyrilli</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Contemporary with <hi>Cyrillus,</hi> with whom he had ſome ſharp diſputes, about the acts of the firſt Councill of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> wherein he was preſent; and afterward he was called to the Councill of <hi>Chalcedon. Pareus</hi> ſaith, that he dyed not very Aged; but <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> tells us, That he was a very old man before his death, his diſſolution happening about the yeer of Chriſt, 450.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:154025:39"/>
               <head>Junilius Afer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IUnilius Afer,</hi> was a Biſhop in <hi>Africa,</hi> the cities name is not known certainly, where he exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his government. He lived (ſaith <hi>Sixtus Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis</hi>) under the Raign of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, about the yeer of our Lord, 440. he was inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate with <hi>Primaſius</hi> the learned Biſhop of <hi>Vtica,</hi> and the Diſciple of <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> By whoſe perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and encouragements, ſome ſay, he did col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect thoſe Explanations upon Geneſis, for the inſtruction of ſuch, as were unskilfull and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned in the Scriptures, which work of his he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to the ſaid <hi>Primaſius.</hi> Some report that he wrote other Treatiſes, but <hi>Trithemius</hi> makes mention that the never ſaw any other but this.</p>
               <p>I meet with two Characters beſtowed on this man, the one is from <hi>Trithemius,</hi> who ſtiles him, <hi>Virum in Sacris Scripturis valde doctum, inq ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laribus diſciplinis ſufficienter inſtructum, ſenſu pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundum, eloquio dulcem, &amp; ornatum.</hi> A man very learned in the Holy Scriptures, and ſufficiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in humane diſciplines, deep or profound in his ſenſe, ſweet and comely in his expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>The other Elogie, and much of the ſame ſound, is from <hi>Sixtus Senenſis,</hi> who calls him, <hi>virum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis artibus in ſeculo eruditum, &amp; in Scripturis Sanct is peritiſſimum, eloquio brevem, &amp; ſenſu acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</hi>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:154025:40"/>A man learned in the liberall arts, and moſt skilfull in the ſacred Scriptures, ſhort in expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and acute in Senſe.</p>
               <p>Some ſay, that that little Commentarie on the firſt Chapters of Geneſis is none of this <hi>Iunilius</hi> his, but that reverend <hi>Beda</hi> is the author thereof, becauſe it quotes <hi>Gregorie,</hi> and is reckoned among the workes of <hi>Bedae. Bel. de Scrip. Eccleſ. in Iunil. p.</hi> 246.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Salvianus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAlvianus</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Marſeilles</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> ſtyled by <hi>Sixtus Senenſis, Epiſcoporum ſui temporis Magiſter,</hi> The Maſter of the Biſhops of his time: he lived about 460. yeers after Chriſt, or as ſome others will have it, 480. It was about the time, when the Northerly people of <hi>Gothes</hi> came down into <hi>France</hi> and fearfully overrun it, which ſad opreſſion canſing the people of thoſe parts to doubt of Gods Heavenly Providence in the worlds government, gave occaſion to this learned Prelat to write that good and excellent book of his, <hi>De gubernatione Dei,</hi> wherein he ſheweth that it is a juſt, and tighteous thing with God to puniſh ſinfull men, which knowing well what they are to do, are yet negligent performers of their duty; which little work of his he dedicated to <hi>Salonius,</hi> who was at that time Biſhop of <hi>Vienna.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:154025:40"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Trithemius</hi> calls this man, <hi>Virum in divinis Scripturis eruditiſſimum, &amp; in ſecularibus literis ſufficienter inſtructum,</hi> A man moſt learned in the holy Scriptures, and ſufficiently skill'd in humane and ſecular learning; agreeing with that of <hi>Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Senenſis, Divina &amp; humana literatura copioſe inſtructus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The foreſaid Hiſtorian ſpeaking of his Epiſtles, ſaith of them, that they are <hi>Sale ſapientiae condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae,</hi> ſeaſoned with the ſalt of wiſdom.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Sixtus Senenſis,</hi> in reference to all he hath written, tells us, <hi>Quod ſcripſit Latino candido &amp; ſuccincto ſermone, multa laudatiſſima opuſcula;</hi> That he wrote many commendable works in the Latine Tongue, both candidly and ſuccinctly. He was the Maſter of <hi>Veranius</hi> and <hi>Salonius,</hi> both of which were alſo Biſhops: So <hi>Gennadius</hi> reports in his <hi>de viris Illuſtribus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>
                  <hi>Proſper</hi> of <hi>Aquitain.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PRoſper</hi> of <hi>Aquitain,</hi> ſo called, (not as ſome think from his Biſhoprick, for he was Biſhop of <hi>Reimes,</hi> but from the place of his nativity, he being an <hi>Aquitain</hi> by birth) lived about the year of Chriſt 460. in the Reign of <hi>Leo Auguſtus;</hi> he wrote excellent Tractates, his Sentences are met with among the Works of <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> He ſhewed himſelf a moſt fierce and ſharp impugner
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:154025:41"/>of the hereſie of <hi>Pelagius.</hi> Beſides his Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical writings, he was the Author of a Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, mentioned by <hi>Gennadius.</hi> He ſucceeded in his Epiſcopal See to the Biſhop <hi>Faventius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Trithemius</hi> thus w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ites of him, <hi>Proſper Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Rhegienſis, vir in divinis Scripturis eruditiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; in ſecularibus nobiliter doctus carmine excellens, &amp; proſa, eloquio diſertus, ſenſu profun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, ingenio ſubtilis, aſſertione nervoſus, vita &amp; converſatione ſanctiſſimus apparuit. Proſper</hi> the Biſhop of Rheims, appeared to be a man moſt learned in the divine Scriptures, and nobly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in things that were Secular, excellent both for verſe and proſe, eloquent in ſpeech pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found in ſenſe, ſubtile in wit, ſinewous in aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and holy in life and converſation.</p>
               <p>He wrote a book <hi>de Ingratis Of Unthankeful men;</hi> by which name he alwayes meant the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagians,</hi> which ſprung up out of the aſhes of that Arch-heretick <hi>Pelagius:</hi> So Biſhop <hi>Uſher</hi> writes in his eighth Chapter <hi>de Primord. Britan. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith this of him to his honour, <hi>Quod multa praeclara ſcripſit pro gratia Dei con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Pelagianos:</hi> That he wrote many excellent things for the grace of God againſt the Pelagians; <hi>Se<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Auguſtini diſcipulum, &amp; defenſorem acerri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum demonſtravit;</hi> and proved himſelf to be a diſciple, and moſt ſharp defender of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> ſtyles him, <hi>Virum acris ingenii, dictionis preſſae, &amp; nervoſae, &amp; elegantis;</hi> A man
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:154025:41"/>of a piercing wit, of a brief, ſinewous, and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant elocution.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Petrus Chryſologus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PEtrus Chryſologus</hi> was Archbiſhop of <hi>Raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> born of Noble Parentage, ſtyled by <hi>Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Senenſis, Vir tam vitae ſanctitate, quam omni eruditionis genere excellens,</hi> A man excelling as well for ſanctity of life, as for all kinde of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. He was inſtructed in Chriſtian literature by <hi>Cornelius</hi> a certain Biſhop, and advanced by Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the third, to that eminent dignity at <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this mans time, there were two Councils ſummoned; the one by <hi>Coelius Symmachus</hi> the Pope, the other by <hi>Theodoricus</hi> the King of the <hi>Oſtrogoths;</hi> the one ſitting at <hi>Rome,</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at <hi>Ravenna.</hi> This Prelate was called to both: And beſides, he delivered Letters to the Council of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> againſt the heretick <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyches;</hi> which Letters are yet extant. He had the name of <hi>Chryſologus</hi> given him, becauſe he was ſo near in conformity to <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> there being in both of them <hi>par phraſium majeſtas,</hi> a like majeſty of phraſe.</p>
               <p>In the Epiſtle prefixed to this mans Sermons,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:154025:42"/>you have this commendation beſtowed upon him, <hi>Si cum hoc quoſdam Neotericos, aut commentatores conferas Pigneum Atlanti comparare videaris:</hi> If you confer any of your Neotericks or late Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentators with this Author, you may ſeem to compare a Pigmy to <hi>Atlas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtus Senenſis,</hi> ſpeaking of thoſe hundred two and twenty Sermons preached by this Prelate, he doth thus expreſſe them, <hi>Breves quidem, ſed ſenſus gravitate venerandes, candore ſermonis, venuſtiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> verborum floſculis amaenos, argutis quibuſdam ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiolis naturali quadam facilitate fluentibus ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundos, &amp; validis quibuſdam affectibus interdunt verbis tragicis expreſſis admirandos.</hi> Short Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons indeed, but yet for the gravity of ſenſe, venerable; for candor of ſpeech, and beautiful flowers of words, delectable; and for witty ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, flowing with a natural facility, pleaſant; and for ſtrong affections, expreſt ſometimes with tragical words, admirable.</p>
               <p>He dyed about the year of our Lord 500. when he had governed the Church of <hi>Ravenna</hi> 60 years.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:154025:42"/>
               <head>Fulgentius.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FUlgentius</hi> an <hi>African,</hi> &amp; a Citizen of <hi>Carthage,</hi> appeared ſoon after <hi>Proſper,</hi> about the year of Chriſt 500. He was Biſhop of <hi>Ruſp</hi> in Africk, and in his time had hot contentions with the Arians, condemned long before by the General Council of <hi>Nice.</hi> He confuted thoſe which aſſerted the doctrine of Free-will, approving himſelf a puiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant maintainer of the ſervitude of mans will to Sin and Satan, which he had received from <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> or rather from the Scriptures. He was Biſhop of that Church near twenty five years, and dyed piouſly in the year of his age 65. He flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed under <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> the Emperour, and <hi>Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimundus</hi> the King of the <hi>Vandals.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In his life he ſhined with tranſcendent humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and ſincerity, deteſting nothing more, than pride &amp; luxury: He abſtained from fleſh, feeding altogether upon herbs and eggs. He did wear only one garment both in Summer and Winter; this being a uſual ſaying with him, <hi>Corda potius quam veſtimenta mutanda eſſe,</hi> That mens hearts were rather to be changed than their garments. He was ſo far from harbouring of wrath againſt any of his enemies, that being extremely injured by one <hi>Felix</hi> an Arian, and thereupon counſelled by his friends to ſeek a remedy at Law, he ſweetly replied to them, <hi>Chriſtiani eſſe non ulciſci ſeſe,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:154025:43"/>Deum enim ulturum injuriam ſuis illatam:</hi> That its the Chriſtians duty not to avenge himſelf, for God is the avenger of his children.</p>
               <p>In the time of his ſickneſs, his Phyſicians ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing him to bathe much, he replied, <hi>Putatiſne balnea hominis mortalis fata impeditura?</hi> Do you think that baths will hinder the death of a man by nature mortal? And he would have theſe words very often in his mouth <hi>Domine hic da mihi poenitentiam, poſtea indulgentiam,</hi> Lord give me here repentance, and afterwards indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Voſſius</hi> calls this man, in alluſion to his name, <hi>Fulgentiſſimum Eccleſiae ſydus,</hi> The moſt bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſtar of the Church. Its ſaid of him by <hi>Gomarus, Quod ſententiis Auguſtini adeo delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus erat, ut eas pluribus in locis, non tam imitatus ſit, quam expreſſerit,</hi> That he was ſo far forth delighted with the ſentences of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that he did not ſo much imitate them, as to the very life expreſs them.</p>
               <p>One takes notice of ſome of his writings, that they are thorny, ſharp, and piercing, <hi>quaſi aculeos in verbis inſerviſſe viſus eſſet,</hi> as if he had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted ſtings in his words. This is noted chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his Mythologie: whereas (as the ſame au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor well obſerveth) <hi>alia pie quidem, &amp; Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ane ſcripta non tam horrida ſunt,</hi> other of his Works being piouſly and Chriſtianly written, are not ſo rough.</p>
               <p>He was baniſhed with an hundred more Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can Biſhops into the Iſland of <hi>Sardinia,</hi> by <hi>Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimundus</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:154025:43"/>the King of the Vandals, which might be the occaſion of ſo much gall in ſome of his Treatiſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Gregorius Papa.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GRegorius Papa,</hi> called <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, he was conſtituted Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> after <hi>Pelagius,</hi> drawn (as it were) into the Chair by conſtraint. He was a Roman by birth, the firſt of the Popes (ſaith one) that diſcovered an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and lowly minde, who would be called <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus ſervorum Dei,</hi> The ſervant of thoſe which ſerve God. He was wonderfully averſe to that great and proud Title of <hi>Oecumenical,</hi> or <hi>Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Biſhop,</hi> boldly ſaying, <hi>In iſtud ſceleſtum voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulum conſentire, nihil aliud eſſe, quam fidem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere,</hi> That to agree to that wicked denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, were nothing elſe, but to deſtroy the Faith. He ever did acknowledge himſelf the Emperour <hi>Mauritius</hi> his Subject. He maintained diſputes with the Jews, and againſt Hereticks. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by publick Decrees, theſe four Councils, of <hi>Nice,</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and of <hi>Chalcedon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He ſuſtained many afflictions by the Longo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards, who had with violence entred <hi>Italy,</hi> and waſted many of the Churches. He wrote many
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:154025:44"/>books, which were conſumed after his death by them that hated them, a few onely being preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved through the interceſſion of <hi>Petrus Diaconus.</hi> He dyed in the year of Chriſt 606. he is ſaid to have countenanced Images in Churches, although we finde no ſuch toleration in the writings of former Fathers: but no wonder, if being a Monk, he was a Patron of Superſlition and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry; yet <hi>Barthius</hi> gives him this character, <hi>Ejus Homiliae mirifice bonis rebus plenae, &amp; exemplar ſequentium ſeculorum doctoribus,</hi> His Homilies are wonderfully full of good things, and as a copy ſet for the Doctors of the following ages to write after. Nay, <hi>Eraſmus</hi> calls him <hi>ſimplicem &amp; pium.</hi> And again ſayes he, <hi>In Gregorio pluram nullo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fuco picturatam ſanctimoniam agnoſcimus;</hi> We acknowledge in <hi>Gregory</hi> pure ſanctimony, and painted with no falſe deceitful colour.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Martin Luther</hi> doth not without ſome colourable grounds diſparage him, whilſt he hath this paſſage in the 49 Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium <hi>admodum tenuiter cognoviſſe Chriſtum, &amp; verbum Evangelii:</hi> That <hi>Gregory</hi> knew Chriſt, and the word of his holy Goſpel very ſlenderly. The ſucceſſor of this Pope, <hi>Sabinianus</hi> by name, out of ſpight and ſpleen to his memory, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured the deſtruction of all his Works: Of which <hi>Sabinianus</hi> we reade, that he was the firſt Inventer of the uſe of Bells, and of Lamps per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually burning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:154025:44"/>
               <head>Iſidorus Hiſpalenſis.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ISidorus Hiſpalenſis</hi> lived in the yeer of the Lord 630. and dyed in the raign of the Emperour <hi>Heraclius: Geſner</hi> ſaith, that he wrote a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie almoſt on all the Scripture, beſides he wrote a book, <hi>De ortu, &amp; obitu Sanctorum,</hi> Of the birth and death of the Saints, and of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, Paſſion, and reſurrection of our Saviour, together with many Philoſophicall Treatiſes; as of Aſtronomy, Coſmography, and Grammaticall learning; moreover he wrote two books of Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, to ſeverall perſons contemporary then with him. <hi>Iohn Gerſon</hi> doth affirm that the acts of the Councills were collected by this <hi>Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> ſaith, that this man was conceived to have been the Diſciple of Great <hi>Gregorie.</hi> Our Biſhop <hi>Downham</hi> having an occaſion to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion him, tells us, that he was Archbiſhop of <hi>Sivill</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> and one of the moſt learned wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which have been in the Church within theſe thouſand yeers. He is ſaid to have culd, and gathered out of the immenſe writings of the ancient Fathers, innumerable volumes of all Arts, and Sciences. To him in regard of his great Sanctity of life, Annuall honours on the ſixteenth
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:154025:45"/>of <hi>Ianuary</hi> are decreed. <hi>Hildephonſus</hi> compoſed a Catalogue of his works. This <hi>Iſidore</hi> was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Iſidore Iunione,</hi> or the younger <hi>Iſidore,</hi> in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction to another of that name, called <hi>Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore Peluſiota,</hi> who flouriſhed about 450. yeers after Chriſt, and was the diſciple of <hi>Iohn Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He wrote a hundred and thirty Greek Epiſtles now extant (as ſome write) in the Vaticane Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary, wherein he did explain the deep myſteries of the Chriſtian Religion. Cardinall <hi>Baeronius</hi> has inſerted into his Annalls an Epiſtle of this mans, written to the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> in whoſe Raign he flouriſhed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Suidas</hi> doth thus advance him, telling us, <hi>quod una cum ſimplicitate veritatem amaret probaret, &amp; ſine omni ſimulatione loqueretur.</hi> That he loved the Truth with ſimplicity; That he approved of it, and would ſpeak it without diſſimulation or hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy. And <hi>Demſter</hi> gives <hi>Hiſpalenſis Iſidore</hi> this following Elogie, <hi>Grammaticus neceſſarius in que plera<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> quae nuſquam alibi;</hi> A needfull Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marian, in whom there are many things no where elſe to be met with.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:154025:45"/>
               <head>Beda.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BEda</hi> was an Engliſh man by birth, calle <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerabilis,</hi> venerable for his great learning, and gravity, and yet he was miſerably enſnared with Popiſh errours, which in thoſe times had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread like a Gangrene every Nation, wherein there was a poſſeſſion of Chriſtianity, ſo that it might be ſaid, that as the whole world was once called Arian, ſo then it might have been ſtiled <hi>Antichriſtian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet this man, though corrupt in his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and judgement, was very zealous in the duties of his calling, fervent in prayer, labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in reading, writing, and preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. But there is nothing makes more for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation then his noble patience, in bearing thoſe heavy and fearfull agonies, which he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went immediately before his death. He was of great fame in the Raign of <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> the ſecond of that name, about the yeer of Chriſt, 690. He lived as ſome reports, <hi>Vitam longiſſimam,</hi> till he was very aged. He dyed under <hi>Leo</hi> the third in the yeer 731. ſo ſome ſay, but others 734. His works are ſet out in eight Tomes. His Commentaries on <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, he gathered out of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf doth inſinuate by theſe words in the preface of them, <hi>In Apoſtolum quaecun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in opuſculis</hi> S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtini
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:154025:46"/>expoſita Inveni, contra per ordinem tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere curavi;</hi> Whatſoever I have found expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Apoſtle, in the works of S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> I have taken care to tranſcribe them in their order.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Durandus</hi> writes of this <hi>Bede,</hi> that being blinde by reaſon of his great Age, he cauſed himſelf to be led into the villages by certain guides, that he might preach the Word unto the people: and when on a time they carried him into a valley full of ſtones, and his leaders deluded him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that there was a throng of people met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, whereas indeed there was not a man come to hear him, he began to preach very zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly, as was his manner, and when he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded his Sermon with theſe words, <hi>per ſecula ſeculorum,</hi> inſtantly all the ſtones cryed out with a loud voice, <hi>Amen, Venerabilis Beda, Amen,</hi> whence it was, ſaith this <hi>Durandus,</hi> that he was ever after ſtiled <hi>Venerable Beda.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:154025:46"/>
               <head>Johannes Damaſcenus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IOhannes Damaſcenus</hi> was a ſuperſtitious Monk, the diſciple of <hi>Coſmus,</hi> contemporary with <hi>Bede,</hi> who appeared in the Weſt, as he did in the Eaſt. He was for a time mingled with the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racens, and for fear of death committed Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try amongſt them, worſhipping (as they did) the bones of <hi>Mahomet.</hi> He ſtood ſtifly for Imagery, whereupon he was excommunicated in the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council aſſembled by <hi>Conſtantius Copronymus.</hi> He was much converſant in the books of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers, as appears by his Treatiſe <hi>de Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxa Fide;</hi> but if he had been as narrow a ſearcher of the holy Scriptures, he had not fallen into thoſe Popiſh ſnares.</p>
               <p>He was the firſt man that brought Chriſtian Religion to a certain method; in imitation of whom, <hi>Peter Lombard,</hi> ſtyled The Maſter of the ſentences, did the like. He flouriſhed under <hi>Leo Iſaurus</hi> and <hi>Conſtantius Copronymus,</hi> about the year of Chriſt 730.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Suidas</hi> does commend him in theſe words, <hi>Damaſcenus vir doctriſſimus aetatis ſuae nulli eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, qui doctrina illuſtres fuerunt, ſecundus: Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcene</hi> a moſt learned man, ſecond to none of his age, that were accounted learned. <hi>Baronius</hi> cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures him for a vain, empty, light, and lying Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:154025:47"/>And <hi>Bellarmine, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Purgator. cap.</hi> 8. doth diſparage and extenuate this mans authority, and yet he makes uſe of a book of his to prove his Purgatory.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Orations, which this Author did write concerning Images, this is <hi>Baronius</hi> his judgment of them, <hi>Fidem illius ſcripti in multis vacillare, &amp; compluribus ſcatere mendaciis.</hi> Tom. 2. Annal. ann. 31. 675.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Rabanus Maurus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>RAbanus Maurus,</hi> by Nation a German, was the fourth Abbot of <hi>Fulda,</hi> and from that degree advanced to the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Ments,</hi> being the ſixth Prelate which poſſeſſed that Chair. He was ſometime ſcholar to that famous Engliſh man <hi>Alcuinus.</hi> All the while he was Abbot, his Monks hated him, becauſe they ſaw him ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent upon his ſtudies, and ſo neglectful of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advantages and intereſts: Whereupon he left them, and went to <hi>Lewis</hi> the Emperour, and would not return any more unto his Abbey, though much importuned by thoſe his Monks to come, God ſo ordering it for their downfal and deſtruction; for no ſooner was he advanced to his Archiepiſcopal See of <hi>Ments,</hi> but their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:154025:47"/>immediately followed.</p>
               <p>While he lived in his Monaſtery, ſome ſay that he compiled Commentaries on all the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, being encouraged thereunto by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours <hi>Lewis</hi> and <hi>Lotharius;</hi> which he gathered out of the Latine Fathers from <hi>Ierome</hi> to <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Bede,</hi> evermore holding to their ſayings, ſentences, and ſenſes; and in thoſe places where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he did not meet with the Expoſitions of thoſe foreſaid Fathers, he made ſupply with his own: yet withall for diſtinction ſake, that the Reader might know and underſtand, which was his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation, and which theirs, he alwayes ſet the Authors Names to their Annotations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Trithemius</hi> in his Catalogue of famous men beſtows upon him this Elogie, <hi>In omni eruditione tam ſecularium, quam divinarum Scripturarune longe doctiſſimus evaſit, cui ſimilem ſuo tempone non habuit Eccleſia:</hi> He was eſteemed moſt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all manner of erudition, as well ſacred as ſecular: The Church had not his fellow or equal in his time.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> ſpeaks as full, as much in the praiſe of this man, who ſtyles him, <hi>Virum omnium diſciplinarum cognitione abſolutiſſimum, Rhetorem, Poetam, Aſtronomum, Philoſophum, &amp; Theologum, cui nullum in illo ſeculo Germania ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit parem.</hi> A man moſt abſolute in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of all diſciplines, a Rhetorician, a Poet, an Aſtronomer, a Philoſopher, and a Divine, to whom <hi>Germany</hi> in that age could not finde a Peer. <hi>Helvieus</hi> ſaith, that this man flouriſhed in the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:154025:48"/>year of Chriſt 814. others 840. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> calls him <hi>Virum aeque doctum ac pium,</hi> a man equally learned and pious.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Haymo.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HAymo</hi> a Monk of <hi>Fulda,</hi> and near kinſman of the Reverend <hi>Bedes,</hi> was one of <hi>Alcui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> his ſcholars, and ſchool-fellow together with <hi>Rabanus Maurus:</hi> He was choſen Biſhop of <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſtade,</hi> about the year of our Lord 840. He wrote Commentaries on the Scriptures, which he gathered out of thoſe that were before him. He was of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, but yet he is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſo erroneous, as other Popiſh Writers both before and after him: Beſides his foreſaid Commentaries, he publiſhed in ten Books a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory. He continued in his Epiſcopal See about thirteen years; ſome ſay he died in the year of Chriſt 853. and that he lieth buried in that Cathedral.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> ſtyles him <hi>virum ſanctitate, &amp; eruditione inſignem,</hi> a man famous for his ſanctity and learning; and the ſame Author ſpeaking like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of thoſe good Commentaries this man put out, he gives them this following commendation, <hi>Pietate, brevitate, dictionis ſimplicitate, ac per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuitate laudandos,</hi> To be praiſed for their piety, brevity, ſimplicity of expreſſion, and perſpicuity.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:154025:48"/>And further he ſaith of this Expoſitor, <hi>Quod ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatus eſt ferme ſemper in allegoricis, &amp; anagogicis ſenſibus, quos velut ſpiritualis apicula, ex omnium antiquorum hortis, ac pratis florentiſſimis excerpſit, quo legentibus eſſet parata ſaluberrimi mellis co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia;</hi> He was almoſt alwayes converſant in alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorical and anagogical ſenſes, which as a ſpiritual Bee, he gathered out of the moſt flouriſhing gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and meadows of all the Ancients, whereby there might be provided for them which reade him, plenty of moſt wholeſom honey.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Trithemius</hi> in his Catalogue of illuſtrious men, thus pourtrayeth him, <hi>Vir in divinis Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturis eruditiſſimus, &amp; inſecularibus literis nulli ſuo tempore ſecundus, ingenio acutus, ſermone diſertus, vita &amp; converſatione devotus, in declamandis ad populum Omiliis celeberrimis induſtriae fuit:</hi> A man moſt learned in the Scriptures, and for ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar learning ſecond to none in his time; of an acute wit, eloquent in ſpeech, devout in life and converſation, and in declaiming of Homilies to the people, he was of a moſt tranſcendent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry.</p>
               <p>And yet <hi>Eraſmus</hi> doth ſomewhat diminiſh him in theſe words, <hi>Haymo non uno &amp; altero loco deliravit; Haymo</hi> hath doted more than in a few places.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:154025:49"/>
               <head>Theophylactus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THeophylactus</hi> was Archbiſhop of <hi>Bulgaria.</hi> There is difference among Writers concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the time when he lived: <hi>Gerhard</hi> in his <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trologie</hi> tells us, that he flouriſhed when <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> was Pope, and <hi>Diogenes</hi> was Emperour, about the year 1071. though <hi>Baronius</hi> and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſay it was in 880. and others 990. and <hi>Eutropius</hi> 760. But its likely, becauſe he was the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that converted the <hi>Bulgariaus,</hi> that he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſooner than ſome will have him. He wrote Commentaries on the Goſpels, on <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, the Acts, and on ſome of the Prophets, all in the Greek Tongue, which were tranſlated by <hi>Montanus</hi> and ſome others.</p>
               <p>He was an imitator of <hi>Chryſoſtome:</hi> Hence ſaith <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> of him, that he was <hi>in Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtomi lectione diu multumque verſatus, ac detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> much worn, and a long while converſant in the reading of <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> Nay, all his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are reputed nothing elſe but an Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Writings of that excellent Author, and ſo the foreſaid <hi>Senenſis</hi> intimates in theſe words, <hi>Redegit in breve, &amp; apertum compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, quicquid admirabilis ille pater ex aureo ſuo
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:154025:49"/>ore, veluti ex abundantiſſimo fonte, in exponendis ſcripturis ſanctis effuderat:</hi> He did reduce into a ſhort and open Compend, whatſoever that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Father had, in expounding of the holy Scriptures, poured out of his golden mouth, as it were out of a moſt abundant fountain.</p>
               <p>He did ſharply refute the Hereticks of old, but for the errours of the Roman Church in his own time, he did too much indulge to. He had an honourable eſteem of Marriage, and was of opinion, that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhould then appear, when the Roman Empire did begin to ſink. <hi>Eraſmus</hi> gives him this Elogie, <hi>Bulgarius In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpres Graecus recentior, ſed haud quaquam ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus mea ſententia:</hi> The Bulgarian Biſhop a more late Greek Interpreter, but not a bad one in my opinion. 'Tis <hi>Luther</hi>'s, <hi>Auguſtinus, Hila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Theophylactus excellunt:</hi> In Coll. Menſ. cap. 30.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> proves this man ſchiſmatical, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the third Chapter of <hi>Iohn,</hi> he reproves the Latines for believing the holy Ghoſt to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed alſo from the Son.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:154025:50"/>
               <head>Oecumenius.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>OEsumenius</hi> was a Greek Writer, as well as <hi>Theophylact;</hi> but when he likewiſe flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, its controverted by many Authors: ſome ſay be lived about 900 years after Chriſt, others 1000. <hi>Sixtus Sinenſis</hi> tells us, that it muſt be after the 800 year, in regard of thoſe Authors he makes uſe of in his Works.</p>
               <p>This man collected out of the Commentaries of the Fathers Expoſitions on the Acts, the ſeven Canonical Epiſtles, and all Saint <hi>Pauls,</hi> which were rendred into Latine by <hi>Maximus Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus.</hi> Its ſaid, That after this man had ſet out his Comments, <hi>Theophylacts</hi> were not ſo highly valued; the one being ſo much preferred in that way before the other; and he alſo borrowed moſt of his Expoſitions from <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> ſpeaking of this Writer, calls him <hi>Graecum autorem, valde doctum,</hi> a Greek Author, very learned; and further he addes, <hi>In explicandis divinis ſcripturis brevis, apertus, &amp; elegans,</hi> in unfolding or expounding the divine Scriptures, brief, clear, and elegant. One <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulus,</hi> a Prieſt of <hi>Coeloſyria,</hi> has ſome Annotations on the Epiſtle to the Romans, but they are all taken out of this <hi>Oecumenius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:154025:50"/>
               <head>Lanfrancus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LAnfrancus</hi> an Italian by nation, borne at Papia, was Arch-biſhop of Canterbury, and in great eſteem for his profound learning, with our <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour, he was <hi>Berengarius</hi> his great Antagoniſt, and writ againſt him, maintaining the errour of Tranſubſtantiation, which the ſaid <hi>Berengarius</hi> had ſo ſtifly oppoſed: he was one of thoſe 113. Biſhops which were convened by Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> the ſecond at Rome, for the rooting out of that Sacramentall truth <hi>Berengarius</hi> had publiſhed.</p>
               <p>Its a thing obſerved by the Orthodox learned, that before this age of <hi>Lanfrancus,</hi> the Doctrine of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> was univerſally received, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, firſt publiſhed by <hi>Egyppus, Fulgentius</hi> his equal, afterward by <hi>Fulgentius</hi> himſelf, then by <hi>Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> all of theſe being African Divines, and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for their learning. And ſo it continued to be maintained by <hi>Iſidore Hiſpalenſis, Maximus Taurinenſis,</hi> and <hi>Proſper</hi> of <hi>Aquitane.</hi> Nay rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied it was likewiſe by Council, as the <hi>Auraſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane,</hi> and the ſixth <hi>Constantinopolitane,</hi> and before that <hi>Charles</hi> the great governed the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, it was ſtoutly defended by <hi>Bede</hi> a Saxon and his Diſciples, <hi>Alcuinus, Claudius, Rabanus Maurus,</hi>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:154025:51"/>and by many other learned Doctors, for the ſpace of 500 yeers and upwards.</p>
               <p>But now began men to ſwerve from that good and pure doctrine of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and eſpecially about that Article of the Sacrament. Satan by his inſtruments promoting (as <hi>Pareus</hi> expreſſeth it) <hi>immanem illum Tranſubſtantiationis errorem, infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum aliorum fontem,</hi> that huge errour of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, the fountain of many others.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Lanfrancus,</hi> though he had ſo great an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the favour of the Conquerour, as that he ordered all his Affaires both in Church, and State, yet when <hi>Rufus</hi> came to enjoy the crown he had not that influence, for the Nobles of the Realme, out of emulation and envy, had alienated the young Kings affections from him; which occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned his ſickneſſe, whereof he ſoon dyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ranulphus</hi> relates this of him, that it was his ſerious, and frequent deſire, he might dye of no other diſeaſe then a Feaver, or Dyſenterie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in thoſe diſtempers the uſe of ſpeech would continue to the laſt breath; he ſate in his Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>epiſcopal Chaire about nineteen yeers, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the third yeer of the Raign of King <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> calls this man, <hi>omnium ſuitempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, in omni literarum genere doctiſſimum,</hi> of all men of his time the moſt learned in all kindes of learning: and ſpeaking of thoſe works which he hath written, he ſaith this of them, <hi>Quod inter alia praeſtantis ingenii monumenta, reliquit pios at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:154025:51"/>eruditos in totum pſalterium commentarios.</hi> That among many other monuments of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent wit, he left behinde him pious and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Commentaries on the whole book of Pſalms. He flouriſhed when <hi>Henry</hi> the third enjoyed the imperiall diadem, about the yeer of our Lord 1060. So ſaith <hi>Sixtus Senenſis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Anſelmus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANſelmus</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Lanfrancus</hi> in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiſcopall See of Canterbury, who for a Popiſh Writer was a man of great fame in the times he lived, and of no mean repute for his learning, even in the reformed Churches. He was by birth a Burgundian, and advanced from an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot to that eminent Eccleſiaſticall dignity by <hi>William Rufus</hi> then King of England, betwixt whom, and this Biſhop there happened afterwards hot contentions, becauſe the King had put up in his coffers ſome rents of Defunct Biſhops, which the Prelat would ever have peculiar, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propiate to the Church; hereupon he was twice baniſhed out of England, but at laſt returning up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſolemne friendly invitation from the ſaid King, he was received by the people with high acclamations, and great joyes.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:154025:52"/>
               <p>This Biſhop was very much againſt the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the Clergie, which it ſeems was in uſe till his time in England, and he is ſaid to attribute the honour to the Virgin Mother, as he did to our Lord her Son. He fell ſick at <hi>Edmondbury,</hi> and and on the 28th. day of <hi>Aprill</hi> in the yeer of Chriſt 1109. being aged 76 yeers, he dyed at <hi>Canterbury,</hi> whether he had been removed in the time of his ſickneſſe, and was buried at the head of his Predeceſſor <hi>Lanfrancus.</hi> Though afterwards he was taken up, and interred in the eaſtern part of the ſaid Cathedral, which he had in his life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time adorned with a moſt ſumptuous ſtructure.</p>
               <p>This man, becauſe by his notable writings he had advanced the Papal Tyranny, and depreſſed as much on the other ſide the Kingly Soveraignty, therefore did Pope <hi>Urban</hi> Order and Decree, That he and his ſucceſſors ſhould ſit at his right Foot in every General Council; and thus it was proclaimed, when that place was given him, in the open Aſſembly, <hi>Includamus hunc in orbe noſtro, tanquam alterius orbis Papam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtus Senenſis</hi> thus deſcribes him, <hi>Anſelmus vir tam divinis, quam humanis diſciplinis nobiliter excultus, ſtylo mire ſimplici, &amp; puro, ſed non in jocundo?</hi> His life was written by his intimate friend <hi>Edinerus.</hi> He wiſhed, when he was dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he might have had a little more time here allowed him, till he had perfected that moſt obſcure Problem of the Souls Original, which it ſeems he had in his life-time taken in hand to determine; but ſayes one of him, <hi>Hoc tempus
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:154025:52"/>datum ei non eſt, ut majus bonum in aeternitate ei daretur:</hi> This time was not given him, that a greater good might be given to him in Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="character">
               <head>Bernardus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BErnardus</hi> Abbot of <hi>Claraval,</hi> flouriſhed in the time of the Schoolmen, and yet is rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned as one of the Fathers, for his ſanctity of life, and ſoundneſs of Doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chemnitius</hi> ſaith of him this, <hi>Recentiſſimus eſt, vixitque poſt confirmatam Epiſcopi Romani Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannidem:</hi> He is the lateſt Father, and lived af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the Tyranny of the Roman Biſhop was eſtabliſhed: Yet he did much inveigh againſt the impiety of the Pope, his Cardinals, Biſhops, and all that Antichriſtian Clergy.</p>
               <p>Biſhop <hi>Carleton</hi> ſayes, <hi>Utinam tales papiſtas multos, imo vel unum talem hodie haberemus in toto regno Pontificio, qualem</hi> Bernhardum <hi>fuiſſe conſtat.</hi> I would to God we had this day many ſuch Papiſts, nay but one ſuch, as it is manifeſt <hi>Bernhard</hi> was. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſolidly diſputes, (as the foreſaid Biſhop further doth obſerve) of the chief Fundamentals and Heads of Faith, as of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, of the Church, of Mans Miſery, of free
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:154025:53"/>Juſtification, of Grace, of New Obedience; all of theſe againſt the Fables of the <hi>Trent</hi> Council. And, ſaith <hi>Carleton,</hi> Is he a Papiſt, that follows the Catholick Church, and the conſent of the ancient Fathers, againſt the Jeſuites, and the <hi>Trent</hi> Impoſtors?</p>
               <p>Hence it is, that many Princes made uſe of him for deciſion of controverſies, and compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of contentions in the Church. This was he, which adviſed Count <hi>Theobald,</hi> when he ſaw him at great expences in the building of Temples, that he would rather ſupply the houſhold of Faith, and build up the living Tabernacles of the moſt High: He died in the 64 year of his age.</p>
               <p>This is <hi>Eraſmus</hi> his character of him, <hi>Bern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hardus feſtivus, jucundus, nec ſegnis in movendis aeffectibus: Bernhard</hi> is pleaſant, ſweet, and not ſlow in moving the affections. And again ſayes the ſame Author, <hi>Bernhardus vir &amp; Chriſtiane doctus, &amp; ſancte facundus, &amp; pie feſtivus,</hi> in cap. 1. Rom. p. 243.</p>
               <p>This is Biſhop <hi>Mortons</hi> Elogie which he gives him, <hi>In atro Romanae Eccleſiae nocte, fere ſolus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffulſit</hi> Bernhardus, <hi>qui tam doctrinae, quam vitae fuae lumine in multis articulis tenebras pontificias diſpulit;</hi> In the dark night of the Romiſh Church, almoſt onely <hi>Bernhard</hi> ſhined forth, who as well by the light of his doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e, as his life, hath in many Articles ſcattered the Popiſh dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>I will adde no more, but that of <hi>Sixtus Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis,</hi>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:154025:53"/>who ſaith thus of him, <hi>Oratio ubique dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, &amp; ardens, ita delectat, &amp; ardenter incendit, ut ex ſuaviſſima lingua ejus mel, &amp; lac verbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum fluere, &amp; ex ardentiſſimo ejus pectore ignito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum affectuum incendia erumpere videantur.</hi> His ſpeech every-where ſweet and ardent, doth ſo delight and fervently inflame, that there do ſeem to flow from his moſt ſweet tongue, honey and milk of words, and out of his moſt ardent breaſt, fires of burning affections to break out.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
